okay so today we will we closed our
introductory part of the course and then
we will go to the actual meet with with
a different with the different methods
for for doing for doing research in
empirical software engineering okay
today we will speak about building
theories in software engineering and we
will speak about also which are the
different strategies for for performing
empirical studies in software
engineering last time we saw data
collection methods which is just a part
of the whole research process okay today
we will see the what surrounds what
which are the strategies that are using
also those data collection method but
first let's start with the moral of a
philosophical part let's say of the
discourse that is related to how to to a
general to a general view or how we
build the theories in a in our in our
field so first of all what is the theory ?
a theory is a term that we already used
both in this course and you ofcourse
also know I know yourself and you use it
yourself but what is exactly let's read
"A statement about the existence of some pattern in the entities that belong to a certain context"
"The boundary of the context determines the scope of
applicability of the theory (e.g., all the people in a certain company vs all the C developers of the world)"
this leidos in this case a theory is a
statement about the existence of some
pattern in the entities that belong to a certain context
so basically the key here is "pattern"
okay ? every time there is a "regularity" in the world or
or in a like in my in my area of interest okay ?
I can build the theory and the theory is about entities
entities here is a generic word
that can be translated also as
observable phenomena and includes both
objects or static elements and "events"
so dynamic elements and that belong to a
certain context it is important to
consider that there are regularities
about entities and they are in a certain
context why is important to consider the
context because the context is the
boundary
the scope of applicability of the theory
for example I can build a theory that is
related to the context of all the people
in a certain company or I can be the
theory that is related to all the C
developers of the world so the context
the boundary to which the theory is
referred is different okay so remember
remember this thing theory is associated
to patterns which end two entities and
two specific contexts I considering this
I can have different levels of
sophistication of a theory and it
depends on how much abstract are these
entities considered so how much abtract
are the objects and the events that are
considered they observable phenomena
okay also means how far are them from direct measurable observation so how far are them from thing that I can evaluate with numbers, okay?
here I made three different example that gives you an idea of what is the  different level of sophistication of a theory.
so we have
low level of sophistication for example
this is the theory ninety percent of
force are found in functions that are
longer than 1000 1000 line of code okay
here you see that this is a theory
because it's a pattern it's some form of
regularity in the world because you can
say that 90% of force is something that
happened like in for example in the
context of a company and or in the
context of all the C functions okay here
come again the contest but still it is a
regularity that that I'm stating a
pattern somehow that I I want to frame
with this theory and in this case it's
quite easy to be verified precisely it
can verify to verify quite precisely
because I'm dealing with frequencies and
I'm dealing with real objects okay and
the measurement that I take are quite
are close to
close to the observation so the lines of
code is something that I can count
easily okay and once I have given the
definition of a fault or saw fault can
be identified quite easily okay then I
have another level of sophistication the
desire for example consider this theory
requirements defects can be classified
into unclarity incompleteness and in
correctness first of all here I see that
I don't have numbers okay and this is
the first first issue that makes me
think okay is already it's already more
abstract than the other one okay ? here I
need first of all some precise
definition of the three classes so what
does the unclarity means what does
incompleteness mean what are in
correctness me okay and I have to assess
that all the existing defects okay all
the deficient existing defects in my
context always can be linked to one of
the classes so it can be if I take a
random defect it can be classified if
one of these three classes are the other
is unclear or incomplete or incorrect
okay and not only this but I have to
assess that every person that has to
link the defect to one of this class
actually classify the defect in the same
way or in similar way the verification
of this theory is much more complicated
okay with respect to the with respect to
the other case okay because I I need to
I need to introduce all these other
definitions and context and evaluation
that are less accurate less and
unavoidable rest less precise okay and
then I have I can have even higher level
of sophistication for example but still
speak about the theory and something
that can I can assess and evaluate for
example this case if the team leader is
not sub confidence self-confident
developers loose trust
loose trust first of all here is not
just it's not just dealing with
something that is referred
to an object requirement okay it's
referred to to to a quality of a person
so self-confidence trusts okay what is
self confidence how can evaluate it what
is trust I can how can I estimate this
okay verification of this concept that
are you understand very abstract much
more abstract than the other one that we
were speaking about up to now requires
unavoidably implies that verification of
this theory is much more difficult okay
and especially precise verification of
in software engineering you find all
these different type of feelings okay
software engineering you have to
consider that you will meet all these
different granularities okay and this is
also the interesting thing because you
deal with different different as I told
in the first lecture
you do with a social aspect technical
aspect human aspect emotional aspect but
also numeric and and and software
related in software related aspect okay
so this was what a theory is what a
theory does a theory can do?
this mainly these five things so
1. it can describe
2. it can explain
3. it can predict
4. it can do explanation and prediction and
5.  it can do especially in an engineering design and
action so it can know so it can also
allow to modify the reality okay for
description for when when a theory
describe analyze a problem okay
the product is normally this are
normally descriptions and
conceptualization so a theory can be a
taxonomy and ontology like the case of
the defect types that I that I gave
before okay so the that one was a
descriptive theory okay the the the fact
that the requirements defects can be
classified according to those the
and classes okay app you can also
explain so can allow to identify the
motivation for for something and in this
case you have to consider the example of
the team leader so the the team leader
example tells us the motivation why
people develop a stand to lose trust so
it can it is explained according to the
to the degree of self-confidence of the
team leader okay it can predict so I I
build the model and I predict how things
are in the reality like in the fourth
example so in the example in which I was
speaking about the presence of folds in
that our founding functions that are
longer that 1000 line of code so this is
the model if I found a function that is
longer and times a thousand level code I
can predict that there will be some
force explanation is pretty important so
I find them order so I I find the mother
about the for predicting the folds and I
also find the motivation why longer
function of functions that are longer
that a certain amount of lines are are
more faulty okay or I can do also design
an action with the theory designer
action means that I use the information
to transform a reality this this is the
I don't have the example here but if you
remember in the first lecture I was
giving you an example about testing
resources the one about the developers
that if they code at night they create
more bugs and they are more productive
but they are more productive so the the
solution was the solution theory
actually I called it at that time the
solution theory was to dedicate more
more testing resources to the to the
code developer that developed at night
okay so this is another type of theory
so is a theory is a solution theory
oriented to design an action
remember that the theory can do all
these type of things and and the example
are quite clarifying I guess now we've
seen what is a theory what a theory does
and now we will see what are the
elements okay
the elements are if you want to remember
them you can you can remember also the
typical questions to which to which they
refer so first of all what first first
first question is what and it's let's
let's read here what are the entities is
tara misu in terms of which a theory of
a description explanation prediction and
prescription these are the constructs of
the theory so the eletric element the
basic entities okay that form the theory
are called constructs we use this term
later on okay then there is a question
how that as a that is referred to how
these constructs are related okay what
are the relationship and the second
thing that that builds a theory are the
propositions so statements about the
interaction between constructs by
constructs I will give you example later
on we intend basically if you're if you
are confident with the entity relation
if a relationship diagram all the
entities so it can be objects but also
attributes okay the constructs so we
will see some example a zero okay so we
have concerts prepositions and the
preposition can also lead to prediction
of course but here just remember
concerts and preposition and there is a
third question that that is why a
certain relationship holds so this is
what gives theory explanatory power we
will see this you know in the next slide
and in the end I have a several other
questions which are aware when and for
whom that are the scope condition that
you didn't identify the circumstances in
which the theory is applicable so these
question is addiction a question are the
context so construct propositions the
answer to the question why motivation
for which certain relationship also the
explanation okay and scope condition
concepts prediction explanation a scope
condition we will see example of these
elements very soon so constructs
construct what concept has the elements
okay here are example to give you a
flavor of what is what is what we intend
here
UML based development methods if you
don't know what is UML you can check
internet but is the basically a set of a
set of diagrams that are oriented to
design software for mostly for object
oriented design okay and the development
method based on UML consists in using
this diagram to guide the development of
software so for creating the the
software design and architecture that
that allows them to develop from that
that is the blueprint for developing the
soft okay but also costs communication
design documentation testability so
these are all concept okay all the
constructs are concept that are relevant
for my research and I relevant form a
theory okay proposition how how the
construct interact for example here
there is a list of proposition this is a
proposal p4 is a proposition for example
the use of a UML based development
method positively effects documentation
so using this method you have a better
documentation this is a proposition
because it relates UML development
method with another with another
caustics with concert which is
documentation okay explanation
explanation is the third component as
and explain why why this relationship
before old hold
the documentation is more complete more
consistent because there is the more
traceability between models and code it
means that I can trace the blueprint so
the diagrams with the actual codes more
understandable more readable so there
are justification for the truth of the
proposition okay and the scope condition
so the other the answer to the other
question you have to remember when where
and whom but the thing that is actually
relevant is more thinking also about the
the actual context the thing that
characterized the context of my theory
for example for this theory this theory
is supposed to be applicable for
distributed projects in which the
operation our creation modification of
embedded safety critical system based on
legacy code or new code so quite a wide
range of system but clearly here it
refers to embedded systems ok so this
theory for example is not applicable is
applicable for software that goes in a
car or in a you know in a in a train or
in an aircraft but is not applicable or
at least it was not verified in a
context of financial systems or like or
systems that for for the public
administration ok
ok in this example and it is the
important thing to consider I am
answering all the questions ok but most
of the time you leave out you leave out
too why very frequently ok so a theory
in principle should answer all this
question ok but very often the
explanatory power so the the way a
theory is able to explain why is is very
frequently quite weak and you often need
more studies for developing an answer to
how and an answer to why ok so this is
for the elements then we want to
understand how theories are formed
there are several strategies okay for
performing theories and you will see
that our method the method that that we
will study are applying one or more or
more of these strategies
okay so first strategy is is the
induction okay I take an observation I
observe the reality and I infer a
generalized conclusion from particular
instances so take an observation of over
set of developers and I start developing
the theory so identify first the
constructs than the proposition the
explanation and the scope okay and the
context from the theory I can deduce
some hypothesis I can define some some
possible hypothesis that will be derived
directly by my proposition okay and then
I have to attest hypothesis so this is
the second step that is deduction and
deduction means taking the proposition
of the theory derive testable hypothesis
you will see testable hypothesis in the
next lecture like a large set of example
and then you have to verify that
actually deals Deportes are true by
observing the reality so you compare the
hypothesis against the reality when you
have built the theory through this
through this iteration okay so you have
inducted and you have elicited some
information and you have deduced
testable hypothesis for the theory then
you may want to extend the theory to to
other feet for example you've developed
the theory for the one that I want that
I was showing before for embedded system
and you may infer that that theory may
be applicable also in the context of
public administration system then I
deduce new hypothesis and I test them in
the public administration system so this
is the way the sig cycle works so I
start normally from induction but very
frequently there is already some theory
around so some information around
so some some preposition that I need to
that I need to verify from this I
there's reduce I bought this I test them
in my environment and when I have some
solid theories or referred to similar
context I can abduct so I can use the
method of abduction and in take a more
creates let's say a more general theory
and port it to another context okay I
port it to another context and derive
new hypothesis and perform a new test
and observation okay yeah and derive new
testable hypothesis for a theory also
for through the second step of deduction
so remember this induction comes from
observation to theory deduction comes
from theory to hypothesize and abduction
from accounts go from theory to theory
okay how do I evaluate the theory once I
have developed my theory how can I
evaluate it here are six criteria for
1. Testability
The degree to which a theory is constructed such that empirical refutation is possible
evaluating it okay first of all
testability
so a theory is somehow scientific if if
it is built in such a way that it can be
falsified okay it can be tested you can
be tested we will see this falsification
concept later on here I I wanted to
leave it I wanted not to focus on it
because it is more related to the way we
test quantitative theory but in any case
testability is is a theory that can be
can be put against reality and we can do
some empirical refutation okay ?
2. Empirical support
The degree to which a theory is supported by empirical studies that confirm its validity
3. Explanatory power
The degree to which a theory accounts for and predicts all known observations within its scope, is simple in that it has few ad hoc assumption, and relates to that which is already well understood
Explantory power : to what extent my theory explain WHY?
empirical support : how many studies are supporting
it how much information from empirical
studies that are actually supporting my
theory then I have explanatory power
that is to assistant my theory explains
why
okay explain why question
so if I considered all the possible motivation that may have lead to this to this
conclusion or I might lose in something
so in there for example in the example
before in which I have the the list of
the list of reason why UML allow UML
makes makes documentation better I may
have I have my F mister some some other
some other variables that might have
influenced my my outcome and so there
may be different reasons with respect to
the one that I found for explaining my theory
4. Parsimony
The degree to which a theory is economically constructed with a minimum of concepts and propositions
okay parsimony so how much how
much fo did I make to to minimize the
number of constructs involved in also
5. Generality
The breadth of the scope of a theory and the degree to which the theory is independent of specific settings
proposition generality so how large is
the scope of material many context am I
am i covering with this theory and
6. Utility
The degree to which a theory supports the relevant areas of the software  industry
utility utility is very important for
our domain because the knowledge that i
acquire through the empirical software
engineering research it needs to be
useful okay it needs to have to a
certain extent to some applicability so
the as it was shown in the first lecture
the path is always arriving to a
solution theory to a theory that is
oriented to transform the reality okay
this is this is a peculiarity of
software engineering theories okay to
consider how useful can baby it is
always not always easy to say okay this
theory is useful and this is not but it
is it is important to reflect and to
make some arguments why it could be
useful okay because it is true that
science and many things that we
developed through research the their
utility may not be self-evident okay
but in software engineering research you
have to argue since it's not fundamental
research in research related to company
to weight people to the way people
behave to code into something very very
concrete very very practical utility is
very relevant ok so how do I formulate
theories this is a step to step guide of
course as you may have known from from
your experiences software developers
thing never works step by step of course
but to to somehow communicate them we
need to we need to use the we need to
pretend that they are working step by
step okay so first of all we need to
define the construct of the theory so
which are the building blocks so this
can be another construct so or existing
one so taking from existing theories
that I want to let I want to take as as
a reference or they can be refinements
of a existing one so I take constructs
from other theories from other from
other research from other literature and
I refine them okay so for example in the
case UML development methods I may want
taking that theory I may want to
consider only one type of diagram the
class diagrams okay to which a stand the
class diagrams for example help in
improving documentation okay this can be
a way of taking a theory and trying to
build on that by refining by refining
the cost art or I can I can use norther
constructs that are somehow related to
the previous one for example another
type of diagram
another type of another type of
development style so this this this is
to tell you that every time you build
the theory you may take also
subconsciously inspiration from some
theory that already exists it is good
that you make it explicit when you
define the theory
what are the drivers and what are the
sources from which you are taking your
constants okay then you defy proposition
again that can be novel they can be
modification or refinements of the
existing ones and and basically they
connect our caustics that our
relationship then I can provide
explanation to justify the theory so a
series of assumption and logical
justification and this is planation they
can refer to existing theories and they
can come also from other disciplines so
the possible explanation so again an
explanation is related to an Acosta okay
there is a motivation that is X that
explain a relationship between concepts
okay and the it is represented here the
explanation is the source of this
relation is this other cost or
activities it is this other element okay
and finally the finder scope of interest
okay the fourth the fourth element that
are the value Co values of the
constructs and their combination dedi
theory is oriented to explain okay we
will see that there is a difference
between the scope of interest and the
scope of validity but in an hour here we
are interested in want what we are
oriented to explain with our theory
remember that every time yeah you you
apply an empirical method you are
actually building theory so your goal is
always to build a theory with a
different with a different flavor so
descriptive explanatory predictive but
still your bidding theory after I built
this theory I need to test it okay
otherwise there's no empiricism okay I
have to evaluate how valid is this
theory and this steps are this one I
have to research I have to select a
research setting and sample by sample
here I mean not just actors but activity
system so all the things all the
components that that I can use in
reality to to identify
Cass constructs and and to test my
theory okay research setting here it can
be like for example a company or can be
a laboratory yeah we will see in the
different in the different examples of
research types in research strategies
that different settings are possible
more natural or more contrived so more
artificial like a lab is an artificial
setting a company is a more natural
setting okay then i io / externalize
theoretical construct into empirical
variables so I transform these contracts
in variable that they can be measured in
reality so a term like testability or
documentation quality needs to be
measured okay and then I translate this
into theoretical problem the theoretical
proposition so the propositions that are
belong to the theory into hypothesis as
I was saying before so I transform this
proposition in hypothesis that I can
test the hypotheses are expressed in
terms of empirical variables and this is
typical of qualitative studies okay but
the philosophy is very similar also for
quantitative side study so is is
something that that you have to consider
for any type of theory okay and then I
have to test the hypotheses so I have to
verify that these hypotheses actually
actually holds for for my for my context
okay and when we speak about the
Protestant testing is always we always
refer to quantitative statistical tests
but as I was saying before this process
applies to both quantitative a
qualitative method although the
terminology is like empirical variable
and precut testable hypothesis and
testing the hypotheses are really mostly
for quantitative studies and and
experiments especially okay
and finally the finder scope of validity
okay I have tested I have selected a sample
and therefore I didn't I didn't
verify my theory for the whole possible
set of samples but just for a specific
set of cases okay
scope of validity is the part of the
scope of interest in which the theory
has actually been validated okay so here
is the summary in terms of a graphical
summary of how the theory is built
according to the steps that I gave you
before so first of all the constructs
the propositions explanation and then
the scope of interest okay then given
this this is the feeling from which I
start I operationalized the variables
and I transform and identify my
apophysis that are basically the
representation of the proposition in
terms of the concrete variables okay and
identify the sample you already see that
this sample is smaller than the than the
context of the theory okay
and then I here I'm still somehow in an
abstract space but closer to reality the
final step is data collection and
measurements in which I actually go to
the reality and collect this data once I
have defined the sample I can apply the
sampling strategy and I can identify oh
my data with the different data
collection techniques that I explained
you last time at this point sorry this
point I can have in my daughter I can
test whether my effort as you sold so
given my data I said hey is this
hypothesis true or not I can confirm and
reject the hypothesis and therefore
support or not support my theory and I
can identify my scope of validity so
after I am verified in a certain
specific context and I have identified
the scope abilities I can say okay my
theory
for the specific context the scope of
validity here you have an interesting
image that tells you that you to cover
the scope of interest of a theory
you know you need multiple studies they
make over different scope of validity ok
so here you have a scope of validity for
study one for study to study three and
all together they cover a part of the
possible scope of interest of the theory
okay
Kress to validity this is another
important point that you will encounter
in every method okay the fact that
you've done all this very nice very nice
process of starting from the theory and
empirical verification etc doesn't mean
that your theory is is accepted or
reject okay you need to provide
arguments that you needed you didn't do
any mistake okay and you need to provide
arguments that you didn't do especially
invalid operationalization of
theoretical constructs and propositions
so for example you need to justify the fact that a constructs successor
says the complexity of the code is
represented with line of codes is it's a
valid operationalization or not you need
to provide arguments okay to which
extent this operationalization is valid
or inappropriate research design so you
may have selected you may have selected
the wrong sample you may have made a
mistake in the data collection
procedures in the data analysis
procedures so you may have made mistakes
across the step and you need to
demonstrate that you didn't do that in
accuracy in data collection and data
analysis this is related to of course to
an inappropriate research design and
possible misinterpretation of the
empirical findings so what you found was
actually clearly leading with the data
and you didn't do any wrong
interpretation
in general each research method as his
own classification that that those that
I listed before where some intuitions
through behind the concept of tres to
validity so anything that you could have
done wrong in this process okay but then
in in in each type of research research
methods you use a different
classification for because you may have
different types of threats different
type of mistakes that you have made and
this is a general classification that is
typical for experiments and that but it
is useful to remember okay because it it
gives you the the flavor of what are the
main concern interest to validity
evaluation
first of all construct validity that is
related to the question that I was
explaining before am i operationalize
the older concert correctly so my
constructs are actually represented in a
proper way by my variables this is this
is the question okay and you have to
provide sufficient arguments internal
validity other any aspects that may have
influenced my outcome and I did not
consider this is related mostly to your
design and data collection method okay
and in this case you have to identify
which are the possible variables that
you didn't control and you didn't
consider and and that may have had an
impact on your design for example if I
am evaluating the complexity of a code
and I'm using some code samples okay and
I want to let the people actual people
assess the degree of complexity of this
code I have to be sure that these people
did not already see the chords that they
are evaluating because otherwise the
evaluation of complexity is biased okay
if you all know already if you've seen
already a certain code of course it will
be less complex than
then for another person who didn't see
it who didn't see it who never saw it
okay these are typical internal threats
so other variable that you did not
consider in your experiment or in your
in your study and that have an influence
all on your outcome external validity
that is related to which extent are my
findings generalizable so this is
related to how much my scope of validity
basically covers my scope of interest or
how many contexts can I cover okay which
for example which type of languages are
considered here in this example
complexity yes but may it be different
from if I if I am covering C code and
Python code so if my experiment is made
on both C code and Python code then I
have quite a good external validity but
if it's just made of one type of code is
more limited okay this is these are
three that are quite clear and I think
quite intuitive as type of threats
okay this we saw in the example before
let's let's make a step back in the
example before we saw this we saw that
we were passing from theory to reality
okay this was the the typical the
typical process for a deductive approach
if you remember the lead early slides
because I'm starting from theory I
assume that I built the theory somehow
and I go towards reality but the reality
could be though so that I don't have a
theory yet so I need to start from
observation I need to start from the
from the reality and in this case I use
the so-called inductive approach so the
one that I showed before is the typical
say if you want the positivist approach
for constructing constructing theory so
the deductive one you start from some
constructs from the lead shutters from
trip
positions and you create hypothesis and
your new test but in our in our diagram
which also the inductive process okay we
will not cover here abductive processes
but inductive is important because it's
typical of the so called constructive
constructivist approaches that are one
the ones using used in qualitative in
qualitative studies so in this case I
start from simple definition and data
collection for example I collect some
interviews in a company and then from
these interviews I identify which are
the constructs okay then I I sold the
basic thing is that I start from my
simple definition and then afterwards I
identify variables and propositions okay
and from this I can build my theory so
the theory comes afterwards I am
eliciting the theory from from the data
okay I can combine the two approaches of
course because in a case in which I
don't know much about a certain reality
like the reality of a specific company
and I have to start with the collection
of interviews before knowing what is
actually relevant what what time for
example in the case that in the example
before what are the elements that may
affect the day or in which way the UML
language can affect the development to
understand the ways I have to treat to
ask to people to understand that till
for example it affects documentation it
affects the stability or rather or other
aspects okay then I have built the
theory in an inductive way but
afterwards I have to test the theory and
I can apply a deductive approach okay I
can take my preposition I can
operationalized in into more refined
variables for example into more measure
measurable variables so give a way of
evaluating the quality of documentation
then I do again a round of some
definition and out of election and in
this case I do my POTUS is testing so I
reduce my policies I test processes and
then I can refute on confirm the theory
so inductive process and deductive
process are combined and are made of
different steps of the field of the
theory constructions and they are used
at different stages okay in one case I
use the inductive processes if I don't
know anything about about a context and
I use a deductive process if I if I
already have some theory or I can build
something from the information that I
have already collected this remembers us
when we were speaking about the
different research questions okay
because theories are built and are
guided in a hidden way here in this
presentation also by research questions
okay when we were thinking about the
research question we were thinking about
exploratory explanatory so different
type of questions depending on how much
information do I have about a certain
context and this is strictly related to
this to this diagram first of all I will
have exploratory research questions and
I always tend to induct I will tend to
use a research approach that is more
inductive once I have the theory
I will go towards more explanatory or
more predictive predictive research
questions and I will tend to use
deductive approach okay
now I'll give you an example in here I
was hiding the example between the lines
but this is the example basically this
is taken from the paper that I used as a
reference here for for building this
this lecture and I invite you also to
read the paper because of course it
contains much more information that I
wanted that the one that I could give
here here the example is
with a field study a field study so I
study in a company basically to
investigate benefits and challenges of
the use of UML in a large distributed
development process so development
project so you have large and
distributed means that you have
different people working in different in
different areas so for example one is in
Milan where is in Florence or even one
in India one in Italy okay so different
teams belonging to the organization but
located in different geographical
locations and you want to understand
whether this UML works fine or not so
what are the benefits and the challenges
and the project was concerned the
project that they were developing is
concerned with a safety critical process
control system okay you don't this is
needed just to identify the scope later
on in this case you are four sites in
three countries so not just Milan
Florence but other country for example
in Germany and in France and you have
many people two hundred and thirty and a
hundred of them are using actually a UML
ok so they put they could collect
information from individual interviews
questionnaires and project documents so
the data collection was using different
strategies okay both interviews
questionnaires or surveys and also
document analysis okay also taking the
documentation so you see already the
data collection strategies that I
explained you before they come they come
handy you have here some people
intensive people intensive data
collection methods like interviews and
some system intensive all objects
intensive like project documents okay
first I define the constructs and to do
that I perform a series of interviews
okay and I from this interview that I
performed with the people in the company
identify which are the most significant
concepts okay and how do I do that
you
learned this when we do qualitative
study and basically it's a strategy
called open coding that means
lovey-lovey in the concepts in the
Inditex finding representation finding
fragments in the text that represent my
my concepts okay so if people for
example like in a trivial case they
mention that documentation many time
documentation may may be relevant and so
this is one of my constant okay and I
can find it
during the interview okay they are
speaking about documentation and so this
is a relevant constructs these are the
examples the same way that I gave you
before so code UML based development
methods is a constructs because we are
speaking about that cause communication
design documentation so these are all
the building blocks that I want to
consider in my theory and that are
elicited they are identified in the
interview transcripts okay in their
interview with the people people are
speaking about this thing so they are
elements that I need to consider my
theory propositions propositions still
from these interviews I can identify not
just the elements but also the
relationship again the paradigm of
entity relationship diagrams is is still
relevant here like you have identified
the entities and now still in the
interviews you identify the relationship
and these are translated into
propositions okay now I have a series of
relationships for example UML decrease
in the effects cost so increases costs
and I want to understand whether this
proposition that I gathered from the
interview are actually true for for all
the people because the interview some
people may mention this aspect and some
people may not so I need to test this
with questioners this this preposition
to make them more solid okay then I
provide explanation display I see that
the in the interview there is some
explanation that explained the reason
behind
position okay and but in some cases for
example I may have no explanation so I
perform further interview that are more
focused on finding explanation for
certain statements of the of the people
and that allow me to list the
destination for example Here I am the
illumination is more complete more
consistent more readable because it
makes it easier to find specific
information to a common format more
understandable for non-technical people
so if I have the diagram it is more
understandable because technical people
find it easier to understand the diagram
that the technical written that the
technical text okay it may be viewed
from different expressed paired
different perspective because I have
different types of diagrams so these are
all motivations that I can find in the
interviews so we are at the step 3 now
step 4 it is define the scope of
interest of the theory so with this
theory in principle what do I want to
cover okay I started from a specific
company's company large company what do
but my inspiration my aspiration is that
I want this theory to hold in a large
broad scope ok that is the scope of
interest so my theory the scope of
interest in general in software
engineering can be defined according to
these four elements one is the
technologies that I consider it
considering and it is UML in this case
the actor the actors that are involved
and here are designers in distributed
team so this characterized my my actors
software system here the type of
software system in amber is embedded
software large-sized embedded embedded
software and activity activities in this
case create a modify UML diagram so if
the editing of I could could also have
called activity tasks for example tasks
that I'm doing is designing
okay design software design finally I
need to test the theory so I've done all
this interview all this step in
inductive way because I was following an
inductive process starting from the date
of the interviews and eliciting
proposition and theory but then I now I
I have the theory but this theory is not
fully robust let's say because I need to
to prove it ok it's not proved I need to
to bio to verify ok and in this case I
apply deductive step that is that means
that I take the single proposition or a
subset because probably to verify with
quantitative methods a deductive
approach I cannot consider all the
proposition all together but better to
focus on one at a time and translate
into hypotheses and do some do some
study ok for example I can use I can
take the proposition use of um add
methods increases costs and I can decide
to assess whether these hypo with is
this preposition that can become an app
or can be translated into an ecologist
it's true by doing by using different
methods for example I can do a field
study sorry for the typo here but is
field study an experiment or a survey
for example if I do a field study I can
identify companies that want to
introduce UML and establish a clear way
to evaluate the cost so I say ok men our
is my way of evaluate cost I consider
another comparable company that's not
using UML and I check the resulting cost
of the two companies so here I am
studying in the real world someone that
is introducing UML and someone that is
not and I compare the cost if the one
that is introduced in UML is is having
higher costs then I can I can I can say
that it is true it is at least it is not
false that the use of your main methods
increases costs okay then
then I can or I can do I can choose to
do an experiment for example an
experiment still related to the same
proposition in this case I take two
group of subjects I give them a
requirements document written in natural
language so that explain basically what
the system should do I ask group one to
take the document and write down the
code and group two to write the diagram
and then implement the code and then I
can evaluate and compare the cost okay
in this case I'm performing an
experiment very narrow take group of
subjects in a lab environment with a
very well-defined requirement document I
have constrained in terms of constraints
since then most are in terms of time it
does not scale - it does not consider
the whole context of a company but still
it's another way to evaluate to evaluate
whether this this proposition is biased
to assess my hypotheses or I can do a
survey a question so with the same
statement I can contact contact multiple
companies that have introduced UML and I
can ask them the same questions that it
asks them to stay their agreement with
with my proposition in this case I can
reach more people and I can I can have
an answer to more than one to two more
than one of these questions but of
course I cannot go too deep into the
reasons for example why someone is
choosing a certain answer or not we will
see that so this this survey and we will
see all this type of study in our in our
in our class so based on this let's
study then identify the scope of
validity that is larger for survey and I
referred narrower for kill study as I
was saying if I am using a survey I am
reaching many more people than if I do a
fit study so if his study is proving
somehow is verifying the hypothesis
testing the hypothesis in a more
restricted context
okay but if I do a survey I am verifying
and testing my hypothesis in a much
broader much larger context okay then
still in this example I as I said before
the these different ways of evaluating
the theory in this case I di assume that
I didn't test I didn't do the theory
testing so I stopped at with the
inductive stage so the testability is
that in this case mmm is a is a ver it
is not so high because it is true that
constructs are well-defined and the
proposition are clear but on the other
hand these are definitions are not
numerical and the data collection was
qualitative so I have I've done some
open coding so I used strategies that
are somewhat subjective so testability
is limited and I could have different
results okay empirical support seems to
be seems to be good because for example
I find other studies that seem to
support my proposition explanatory power
is also is also limited because
motivations are derived from the
interviews so the the reasons why have
not been actually I didn't to consider
all the possible variables that may have
that may explain why okay parsimony yeah
I can consider can give arguments that
the number of constructs is limited the
generality is a bit limited because my
scope is related only to a field study
in a specific company okay but the
utility is very high because you can
help this is you're making so if I am a
cop funny I know that this very large
company has used UML and it has affected
the cost but it has improved the quality
of documentation I can know what to do
if I have money to invest and I know
that in the long term using this
language pays off and this is the
written in a paper from a study of a
large sized company that is comparable
to mine this is extremely useful
okay I don't have to take AI I can take
the risk of introducing you a man so hmm
this theory maybe not so much supported
not so much general but still very
useful okay and these are all arguments
that when you develop a theory when you
do an implicit study like the one
exemplified are all illogical arguments
that have be to be checked by peers so
you write these arguments that these are
just words but the so called reviewers
of your research will we check whether
these arguments are sound okay so there
is the there is a research community a
set of other people that will read your
arguments to support your theory and and
will be allowed to evaluate your work
okay