[Applause]
so I'm going to begin by introducing you
to this guy this is Antoine de
saint-exupéry he was a French aviator
aviator is the word that we used to use
for pilot back when aviation was really
dangerous and it was really dangerous
because the planes crashed a lot he
experienced several crashes during his
career and survived almost all of them
he is once trying to set a speed record
from Paris to Saigon but his plane
crashed in the sahara desert just
outside of Cairo and he was not prepared
for desert survival so he suffered
terrible dehydration as a result of that
he stopped sweating which in the desert
is a really dangerous thing he had awful
hallucinations fortunately he was
rescued by someone who knew how to treat
severe dehydration and he recovered Wow
World War two was starting so he went
into exile in America where he became a
writer it turns out he was a really good
writer he is best remembered for having
written the little prince which is a
famous children's book it's about an
aviator who was stranded in the desert
who was was visited by a strange little
boy who lives on an asteroid and his
suicidal like all the great children's
books it's not really a children's book
he also wrote books for adults and in
one of them he wrote what I think is one
of the best sentences ever written he
said it seems that perfection is
attained not when there is nothing more
to add but when there is nothing more to
take away he was writing about the
design of airplanes but it seems to talk
about everything which combines
discipline and creativity and I hear
this quote being used all the time from
in architecture and design and
everything but I think it has a
particular application to programming
because we have this real connection
with perfection more than any other
craft our programs have to be perfect if
our programs are not perfect in every
way dad things happen and he gives us
some insight as to how perfection is
attained it's not by adding things it's
by taking things away and it occurred to
me that this should also apply to
programming languages that we can make
our programming languages better by
taking away things so that leads to the
idea of good parts where a language can
be made better not by adding things but
by removing things and the principle of
good parts says that if a feature is
sometimes useful and sometimes dangerous
and if there is a better option then
always use the better option I think
this makes a lot of sense a lot of
people still think this is controversial
that you can't make me use the better
option which seems like an odd argument
to make but there's still a lot of
people saying that and I think it comes
from a fundamental misunderstanding of
what it is that we're doing here we are
not paid to use every feature of the
language at the end of a project there
isn't a manager with a clipboard saying
did you use a-plus-plus did you leave
out any semicolons excellent no that's
not what they're looking for we are paid
to write programs that work well and are
free of error now free of error when did
that become part of the deal
well it turns out it has always been a
part of the deal it it's the most
important part it's just that we attain
it so rarely that it's easy to forget
that that's the most important thing
about what we're doing so my advice to
everybody who wants to be a better
programmer is to learn more languages
because a good program good programming
language should teach you and in my
career the language which has taught me
the most was JavaScript
I had a very difficult relationship
relationship with JavaScript because in
the beginning I made every mistake with
JavaScript you can make starting with
the first one the worst one I started
programming without bothering to learn
the language first and I I thought I
could get away with that because it
looked familiar I thought I understood
how it worked and it punished me for
that it punished me hard eventually I
decided to read the standard and try to
figure out what the language actually
did and that completely changed my
understanding of this language it was
not at all what I had thought of at
first it was actually a very different
actually a very good language but until
I read the standard I had no idea that
was true now even though it's a very
good language it's a language that
contains a lot of bad parts and to help
me manage those bad parts I wrote a
program called jeaious lint everybody
should be using jeaious lint you know
all of your code everything should pass
chance lint because it's important for
us to write good stuff and this is the
best way to assure that it's good and
when I started writing jeaious lint
I had no idea about programming style I
didn't think style was important I was
just looking for errors but jeaious lint
taught me that programming style is
actually very important that increasing
the visual distance between a good
program and a bad one is one of the most
effective ways we have to avoid making
mistakes so turns out chance lint is a
lot smarter about javascript than I am
it taught me more than I taught it so I
wrote my own book about my adventures
with JavaScript and giant called
javascript the good parts anyone heard
of this one yeah a few hands go up so
it's still a best-seller in its category
which is really unusual
most software books are obsolete at the
time that the printed in this one has
been out for 10 years and is still doing
really well and I think that's because
it turned out what I identified as good
parts we're mostly right and
so there's still value in the book that
said I'm working on another book and I'm
hoping to get it out for you this year
and in the process of going through it
it gave me a chance to sort of
re-evaluate and decide what actually is
good and what is not there is still an
argument though about good parts that
there are some people who think that
that concept doesn't apply to them
so I'd like to review some of the
arguments about why we shouldn't care
about the good parts the first one is
it's just a matter of opinion you say
it's bad I say it's good all opinions
are equally valid that turns out not to
be true that and the reason I say that
is so I'm the maintainer of Janice Lynch
and I get reports from people from all
over the world an occasion I get
something from someone who says we've
just spent two bloody weeks chasing down
some weird thing that turned out to be
an obscure corner case in JavaScript
that none of us had ever heard of and it
really was expensive to find this thing
could you please put a test in to Janice
lint so that no one will ever experience
that again and if their request makes
sense I put it in which means that if
you're using jeaious lint that will
never happen to you
that's not an opinion that is a fact
every feature is an essential tool I
need to be able to use every tool in the
tool sets in order to do my work it
turns out that's not true
that you can do better work with just
the good parts with just the good tools
you don't need to use the tools that are
rusted or have broken handles if you can
do better work without a broken tool
then that tool was not essential but a
feature is sometimes useful I should be
able to use everything which is
sometimes useful and this sounds like a
good argument except it turns out that
everything is sometimes useful humans
are so creative we can find a use for
anything there's nothing so awful or
does
gusting or bad that we can't find a use
for so saying that something is
sometimes useful is saying nothing at
all because you can say that about
literally everything so if your only
argument for using a feature is that
it's sometimes useful you do not even
have an argument I have a right to use
every feature so this sounds important
we're gonna be righteous now I have a
right and we're gonna fight for our
rights and that's we're gonna do that
but if you take this argument to the end
do you have the right to right to crap
yes I have the right what are we
fighting about that it doesn't matter if
you have the right what matters is you
have the responsibility to write good
programs that are free of error
I need the freedom to express myself I'm
a poet and I express my poetry by
leaving out my semicolons I need to
reduce my keystrokes this is an
important one we think that we spend
most of our time power typing you know
you think over the day what did i do
today I was typing I got that that I did
that $1.00 right of writing a program
da-da-da-da-da except that's not
actually how we spend our time we spend
most of our time staring into the abyss
saying my god what have I done
so it's not the keystrokes it's that you
know if we could figure out a way to
spend less time doing that we will be
much much more productive the keystrokes
are irrelevant you could take all the
clean finished code that you produce in
a year in a day you know if all you were
doing was typing in the program did it
did it
I'm not saying it'd be a fun day but in
a day you could type all the program
that you write in the year that raises a
question what are you doing with the
other 99% of your time it's a lot of its
that then it's an insult to suggest that
I would ever make a mistake with a
dangerous feature obviously someone
who's less qualified than me would make
mistakes with that but I am so skilled
that I can do stupid things and it's
gonna work that that's not good there's
a good reason those features were added
to the language now I've been part of
the standards process so I can tell you
for a fact that is not true there are
all sorts of reasons for why things can
get into a standard and the if they
don't have to be good in order for that
to happen so Brendan Eich who's the
brilliant man who invented JavaScript
talks about foot guns a foot gun is a
feature that you use to shoot yourself
in the foot and he unintentionally put a
lot of foot guns into JavaScript and
they're people who think that they're
there to be used so watch this I almost
always miss here we go so the purpose of
a programming language is to aid
programmers in producing error free
programs if you're doing anything else
you're doing it wrong you're misusing it
so we used to think it wasn't possible
to write good programs in JavaScript so
now don't even try just write sloppy
because that's the best you can do that
turned out not to be true that it is not
only possible to write good programs in
JavaScript it is necessary
because of all the badness in the
language you have to bring an
extraordinary amount of discipline to
the writing in this language that means
you really have to write everything well
so there's a lot of confusion about
JavaScript for example it's crazy name
it seems to have the same name as
another language called Java it's it can
it's confusing it's similar to the
confusion between Star Trek and Star
Wars right you've got two
science-fiction franchises that you know
got spaceships and people fighting and
stuff and basically the same name but
the fans know they're really different
right you can't confuse them in Star
Trek you have phasers and photon
torpedoes uniforms dam regulations and
in Star Wars you have lightsabers and
blasters proton torpedoes sand chaos I
hate sand by the way so when you're
working in Java so which language is the
Star Wars language right it's JavaScript
right so when you're working in
JavaScript it gives you a choice
you can either go Jedi where you can go
Jar Jar unfortunately a lot of our
brothers have decided to go Jar Jar so
I've observed two things the fantasy of
infallibility and the futility of Follis
'no stew a titude x' i find the first
one the fantasy of infallibility mostly
in younger guys who think they can write
mad crazy code and it'll work and
they'll just take ridiculous risks just
cuz and then I see the futility of
thoughtlessness mostly in the older guys
we're saying it never works it's never
going to work why even try so two very
different perspectives but they both
lead to the same thing danger driven
development
where you take unnecessary risks and the
coding just to keep it interesting so
one of the things that makes programming
so difficult to manage is the difficulty
in scheduling in order to schedule
software we have to ant figure out what
time a is the time it takes to write the
code and that's difficult because we're
perfectionists you know ask a programmer
how long will that take
you know it's about that make you stroke
standard you know forgetting about all
that other time but even harder than
that is time B time B is a time it takes
to make the code work right now ideally
time B should be zero right you write
the code and it works right and you're
done but that's usually not the case
time B can be greater than time a right
and I've seen cases where time B is
infinite that's what happens when a
project is canceled after code complete
because they could never get it to work
so we don't want to do that if you're
doing anything during time a which
increases time B you're doing it wrong
so we should always take the time to
code well because if the code is written
well it's going to be easier to make it
work and it's critical even if you're
doing something cheap and dirty
something that's only going to run once
it still has to run at least once and
that's gonna be easier to do if you
write it well don't be sloppy so there
are new good parts in es6 you've
probably heard of them all the best one
unfortunately is not available
everywhere yet it's proper tail calls if
the last thing a function does is return
the result of calling the function
either itself or any other function the
compiler is required to instead of
creating a call return sequence it
instead generates a jump so it's
essentially a go-to with parameters and
this can cause a lot of programs to go
much much faster it also enables
something called continuation passing
style which is a form of programming
that was discovered in the functional
programming scheme which would be really
really effective in JavaScript if we had
this feature unfortunately Microsoft and
Google have been very very slow to
implement this so I'm I'm hoping if you
know any of those people tell them to
get on it
we need this this is the most important
feature we got in es6 second would be
the ellipsis operator or the dot dot dot
which can be used in calling sequences
in in parameter position or in argument
position in parameter position it says
take all of the remaining arguments and
pack them together into an array is so
it's a very effective way of dealing
with functions that need to take a
variable number of arguments in in
calling position it will spread the
array out so that each element becomes a
separate argument so this is two
versions of the curry function it
modified so that can take any number of
arguments the first one is the way you
can write it in es6 the second one is
the way you write it in es5 which one
would yet rather have to maintain
anybody six yeah obviously
so I like that that's good it modules we
got modules which was really good
because browsers provide linkage in the
form of global variables and we know
that global variables are evil
so modules give us an alternative to
that unfortunately module I don't like
the way modules turned out they're much
too complicated
I think modules should be simple where a
module can import whatever it needs and
will export one thing it's going to
export a function or an object
containing a bunch of functions and
that's it you want to have the simplest
interface possible if you have a
complicated interface then it's not a
good module module should surround what
they do be really clean and fortunately
there is a clean subset of the module
syntax
recommend using just that and avoiding
all the tricks and weird stuff we have
let in constant the language let is the
new var the difference between let and
var is that var ignored block scope and
let enforces block scope it turns out
you don't need block scope to write good
programs but if that's all the Java guys
know so if if you just have var on the
language they get confused and that's
not good that's not good right when the
Java guys get confused that's that's
trouble so if we have lot in the
language they don't get confused as much
and that's good so I recommend using
that only for that reason and we also
have Const and that that's good to
actually like Const better because it
discourages the use of assignment which
gets us away from mutability which gets
us a little closer to purity which is
mostly a good thing we have some new
syntax called destructuring
unfortunately that can get too wild too
but there is a simple form of it which I
like a lot where in this case we're
gonna create two variables that in other
and we've got an object on the other
side and that will be initialized with
some object dot that and other will be
initialized with some object not other
this doesn't allow us to do anything
that we couldn't do before but there are
some idioms which are much cleaner much
more readable in this form so I'm liking
this we have week maps week maps are
really important week maps are the way
that objects should have worked in
JavaScript JavaScript only allows
strings to be used as keys and objects
but there are times when you really want
an object to be a key in an object and
JavaScript doesn't allow that but week
maps do so we didn't fix objects we
added an
other thing and week maps also work well
with the garbage collector so if you
have an object and the only place that
exists is as a key in a week map then it
will automatically be deleted so there
are certain forms of memory leaks which
are avoided if you use week Maps the
problem with week map is it has the
worst name of any feature of programming
language ever nobody wants to use
something that's weak right but it's
really good I really like weak maps it
allows us to write programs that we
could not write in the language before
we have mega string literals which are
big I'll show you them in a minute first
let's look at a regular expression
anyone guess what this matches of course
not these don't these are terrible it's
really really hard to read regular
expressions but what I can do is I can
wrap the regular expression constructor
with something which takes a string and
deletes all the whitespace from it and
using the new literals I can now write
it like this so this one you can read
right so what this is is it batches all
of the number literals that are in es6
so we have binary literals octal
literals we've always had the hex and
the floating-point so which one would
you rather maintain the top one at the
bottom one I'm thinking the bottom one
yeah so but it's still a really weird
and a nasty notation I wish we had
something better but we don't until we
get something better and I'm not
confident that we ever will every time I
write a regular expression every time I
run it through regular x regular x is
something on the web which will take a
regular expression and show to you as a
railroad diagram so you trace the train
around the tracks and that shows you
what the thing matches and it makes a
lot more sense than that does
what else we got so we added a lot of
bad stuff in in es6 and it was all well
intended and people had good reasons for
why they wanted it but we shouldn't have
done any of it
so proxies were intended to be a
solution to the no such method problem
but it turned out to be way way too
complex generators were completely
unnecessary if you know how to write a
function that returns a function you
don't need generators in fact I think
you should have to understand a function
that returns a function in order to get
a JavaScript license it's we added
iterators don't need them symbols we
don't need them because we have week
maps whatever you could do with symbols
you could do with week maps just don't
need it reflection we don't need and the
fat arrow functions so that was highly
requested by a lot of the functional
guys and their argument was that the
problem with the function expression was
there was too much typing you had to
type a few NZT that's too much to type
but can't do that I said well there's
this new thing called keyboard macros
you know see just it's too much to read
so okay so we put this in but I don't
like it because it looks too much like a
relational operator so it's I think easy
when you're scanning a program to miss
the fact that this is a function so it
looks like it might be a comparison but
anyway what this one is is it's a little
function we don't have to say return
I'll just return a thing so it's going
to take a name and return an object that
contains an ID property of that name so
we made a tiny little constructor so
that's pretty neat except that this is
not going to return a new object it's
going to return undefined so if you look
at the code is it obvious why it returns
undefined it looks like it should yeah
yeah it's we keep doing stuff like that
we'd pick stuff that looks like one
thing and accepted it doesn't work and
you don't get any warning that it
doesn't work it's just dad so for that
reason I recommend it's just not worth
it for for the number of keystrokes you
save given this potential syntactic
hazard I would just rather not use them
which is a shame now by far the worst
new feature in es6 is class this one was
strongly recommended by all the Java
guys who are having to write in
JavaScript now who don't want to have to
learn a new language and so this gives
them the illusion of writing in a
language that they think that they
already know except we didn't really add
classes to JavaScript it's just
syntactic sugar on top of the prototype
stuff which kind of works the same but
kind of doesn't and so there are some
places where your people that can get
surprised because it doesn't work the
way they think it does and whenever you
have that kind of confusion bad stuff
happens but worse than that if your
content in writing in this style you
will never understand how to use
JavaScript as a functional language and
it's so much more fun and pleasant to be
writing in JavaScript in that way the
people using class will never learn that
will never experience it they will go to
their graves never knowing how miserable
they were so in in the good parts I
recommended that you not use new it you
should use object.create instead and I
managed to get object.create
added to es 5 just so that I could use
it so I was pretty happy about that
so that's kind of surprised when I
noticed that I have stopped using
object.create and the reason for that is
that I stopped using this that if you're
not using this then object.create
doesn't really do much for you and the
reason
for that about this is that in 2007 I
did an experiment called ad safe there
were a bunch of projects including fbj s
at Facebook and website at Microsoft and
kaha at Google and my own ad safe
project we're all trying to figure out
how can we make JavaScript
safe so that we could allow a third
party to run in a page and not get out
of hand
stealing stuff and doing bad things and
the problem everyone had to deal with
was if you have a method and you call it
as a method everything's fine
this gets bound to the object of
interest but if you take that same
method and call it as a function this
gets bound to the global object which
gives away all of our security how do
you get around that so the approach of
the other projects took was doing code
rewriting so they would read a
JavaScript program and rewrite it adding
lots of indirection and runtime checking
to make sure that this didn't get out of
hand my approach was much simpler I said
let's make this illegal if we see a
program with this in it
we won't let it run we reject it that's
really simple to implement and it
doesn't make debugging harder and it
doesn't slow down the code which was a
problem with the other systems the
problem was that zero percent of all
existing JavaScript programs would go
through and so it just said well if you
take away this it's still a
turing-complete language so we should
still be able to do everything that we
need to do so to test that hypothesis
and to get an understanding of how
painful was going to be to do this
transition I started writing in a
dialect of JavaScript that didn't have
this in it and I was very surprised to
discover that it didn't get harder it
got easier and my programs got better
because I I was having to do function
stuff and not doing class stuff and
everything was great so I now recommend
everybody stop using this
I stopped using null so javascript has
to bottom values null and undefined and
there's an argument in language design
should you have any bottom values but
nobody thinks you should have two of
them and javascript has two of them and
people are confused when you have two
things which are very similar but not
the same that creates confusion some
people think you can use them
interchangeably but you can't because in
some cases they behave differently and
that difference is a source of confusion
that causes bugs so I decided to get rid
of one of them and the one that I can
get rid of is null because the system
itself uses undefined undefined is the
value of an uninitialized variable or a
missing property and so that's the one
the system uses and that's the one that
I use I stopped relying on false eNOS
you know the faulty values everything is
either true or false II Brendan did that
because of C C is an under typed
language so C uses a single value 0 to
represent null false the end of strings
0 and some other stuff and Brendon
wanted to be able to do the same kind of
stuff when writing in JavaScript and I
now think that that was a mistake
I think Java got this one right that in
a in a condition that value should
better be a boolean it shouldn't be
bullish I don't use for anymore because
in es5 we got these wonderful new array
methods like for each and map and reduce
and all those others so most of the time
you use a for statement it's because you
want to visit each element of an array
and it's much much better to use these
things you don't have to ever do the
plus plus stuff all of that happens
automatically all you deal with is what
you want to happen for each element it's
a much better way of writing programs so
I stopped using for
I don't use for in because I managed to
get object keys added in es5 so it now
returns a nice array of the own
properties of an object so you don't
have to worry about what might get
credit up on the prototype of chain and
then you can take that array and pass it
to for each yeah it's just a much nicer
way to deal with the stuff and when es6
is finally implemented everywhere and
will have proper tail calls and I will
stop doing a while so here are two
versions of the repeat function you pass
repeat function a function and it will
call that function over and over again
until it finally returns undefined the
first one is using while to do that the
second one is using tail recursion to do
it it's returning the result of calling
itself the yes v or es6 pecked requires
that these both run at the same speed
with the same memory pressure so there
is no longer a performance penalty for
using tail recursion and when that
finally becomes available I will be done
with loops I'm going to be writing all
of my repetitive stuff this way forever
so I've been thinking a lot about the
next language the language which
replaces JavaScript and I believe that
we have to have a next language because
if it turns out that javascript is the
last language that would be really sad
we shouldn't stop there we should find
something better if only for your
children right you don't want your
children writing in JavaScript so what's
the next language is going to look like
and it's not clear it's not clear
because programmers are as emotional and
irrational as normal people now that may
sound really insulting that I'm
comparing you to normal people but it's
true and why do I think that's true well
let me show you my evidence it took a
generation to agree that high level
languages were a good idea it used to be
that all programs were written in
machine language with where you had to
enter every single instruction and it
was a lot of work and very easy to get
things wrong and then Fortran comes
along in in Fortran you just write
things that look like equations they
called it automatic programming at the
time the idea was that the computer
would write its own programs you just
tell it what to do and so it was so much
easier and who would benefit from that
more than anybody else the programmers
and who refused to use it
the programmers had a similar thing
happening with the go-to Dijkstra writes
his letter to the C ACM in 68 suggesting
that goto should be eliminated from all
languages replaced with while in
if-then-else and that starts a bitter
argument that goes on for 20 years and I
remember that argument it was loud and
noisy and crazy people saying you can't
take the go-to away from me it's an
essential tool it's how I express myself
I'm a go-to guy I have a tradition my
grandfather used to go to it took a
generation to agree that objects were a
good idea objects are first discovered
in scheme or and I'm sorry in Simula and
being one of the most important
breakthroughs in programming the world
took don't notice of it at all except
for one grad student at the University
of Utah who thought that this object
idea was so powerful he could use it to
create a programming language for
children and that eventually leads to
object-oriented programming
in 1980 the were 85 I think the industry
had a choice what was going to be the
dominant object right a programming
language it can either be small talk ad
which was the best most carefully
designed programming language in history
or C++ and we chose C++ and that
decision was made by people who
fundamentally didn't understand what
object-oriented programming
and they chose C++ because he didn't
need to understand what object-oriented
programming programming was in order to
use it and we were still paying the
price for that all of our languages
since then have followed the C++
heredity and not the small talk oddity
then it took two generations to agree
that lambdas were a good idea lambdas
were perfected in the scheme language
again in the early 70s and world took no
notice of it and it took so long to get
to the mainstream that some thought it's
never going to go to the mainstream
because if it were a good thing it would
have happened by now but it is happening
now anyone know what the first
programming language was that brought
lambdas to the mainstream any guesses
it was JavaScript JavaScript was the
first one followed by Ruby and Python
and c-sharp and eventually a PHP got it
before Java is that embarrassing or what
so the reason each of these things take
so long is that we don't change minds we
have to wait for a generation of
programmers to retire or die before we
can get critical mass on the next idea I
remember when the go-to thing was going
on and it was really loud and hot and
people are getting really upset and
making ridiculous arguments and then one
day it was quiet so I are they gone can
we get rid of it now yeah we got rid of
it and everything was fine
that during the argument there are all
these complaints about or predictions
about bad things that were going to
happen almost threats that if you get
rid of go to the consequences are going
to be terrible and we got rid of go-to
and everything has been fine
and in fact the major benefit of getting
rid of go-to is that it is easier to
write programs of greater complexity
that having go-to complexity became
overwhelming much earlier that by going
structured we could make programs much
bigger more sophisticated before the
complexity becomes overwhelm
so again who benefited from that it was
us and who rejected it again it was us
so that's why I think it's going to be a
problem with the next language because
when the next language appears we will
all say no no none of that we don't want
that so looking at languages I would try
to put them into two classes systems
languages and application languages the
dominant a systems language is something
you'd use to write a kernel or a memory
manager or a device driver and nothing
else everything else should be written
in application languages and we have a
problem with systems languages because
the dominant systems language today is
still C and C comes from the late 60s we
have lost the ability to innovate in
systems languages right I think that's
shocking but I'm more concerned with
application languages because that's
where we live that's where we spend most
of our time so I would take the
application oh and I think every
language should clearly be on one side
of that line or the other I think the
biggest design error in Java was it
couldn't decide if it was a system
language or an application language and
so it tries to have one foot in each
boat and that's a problem one of the
consequences of that is that it requires
the use of threads in applications which
is a really really bad idea
so you can take application languages
and split them into two classes those
that use classical inheritance and those
that use prototypal inheritance the
classical languages are almost all of
the languages and the prototypal
languages are pretty much just
JavaScript and for a long time I was a
big advocate prototypal inheritance
because one of the problems that you get
with the classical stuff is it comes
with a lot more work first off when
you're designing your system you need to
do a classification you have to identify
all of the different types of objects
you're going to have
and those will become your classes and
then you have to work out the taxonomy
you have to figure out what is going to
inherit from what what's going to
implement what what's going to provide
an interface to what and we're doing
that at the stage of the program when we
have the least understanding of how that
should go together usually at the
beginning you know first we have to
design the hierarchy and then we'll
implement it and because it's such a
difficult problem it's inevitable that
we get it wrong and but we go ahead with
this broken taxonomy and we find that
things aren't quite right that program
or classes don't compose the way we
would want them to and that we find we
wish that we had multiple inheritance
because we just can't get stuff to go
together and that whatever is broken in
the bottom layers starts to work its way
into the higher layers as well that
there's leakage and everything gets
broken and eventually gets so bad that
you think you have to refactor which
means that you have to tear everything
apart and try to put it back together
the right way and that's really scary
because it might not ever go back
together and so we don't want to do that
either and people who live in the
Classical School assume that that's just
inevitable all programs have to live
with that that's just a fact of life and
it's not that's a characteristic of
classical programming and that doesn't
happen in prototypal programming because
you don't have the tight coupling that
classes have with extends and so the
program's just compose much better
so with prototypal inheritance we avoid
all of that stuff and there was another
advantage which is memory conservation
so the major advantage to using
object.create instead of object copy to
make instances is that object.create
uses less memory because we can inherit
properties instead of copying properties
and that may have made a lot of sense in
1995 when the language was design
and doesn't make sense anymore Moore's
law has been so incredibly generous on
memory capacity that the old way of
thinking is completely ridiculous now
you all have at least probably several
gigabytes of RAM in your pocket the way
we should think about memory is
completely different but we're still
programming like memory is a very
constrained resource it's not anymore
it's also a source of confusion because
we have own properties and inherited
properties and sometimes they behave the
same and sometimes they don't
anytime you've got things which are kind
of the same but not you have a source of
confusion which can lead to bugs it also
provides for a retroactive heredity
where we can change what something
inherits after it's been constructed
I've not found any good uses for that
but I've seen some very very bad uses
for that it also tends to inhibit
performance that modern JavaScript
engines get speed by making assumptions
about the shape of objects but they have
to be pessimistic about prototype chains
because the prototype chain can change
without notification so I no longer
recommend prototypal inheritance I'm now
an advocate of class free object related
programming
I think class free object Airy
programming is JavaScript's gift to
humanity so this is block scope you all
know block scope is we've we've got two
blocks each defines a variable a or B
and the inner block can see both
variables but the outer block can only
see its own variable so because a block
hides stuff which is a good thing and
all languages even JavaScript now can do
something like that
and the same thing also works for
functions because a function is just a
block with some extra plumbing on it
which allows the block to be executed
somehow in the future
and we've still got this relationship
where we can diagram the variables so
variable a or the green function has
variable a and the yellow function has
access to a and B and so this concept is
called closure talking about sets that
one set closes over the other set and it
took a long time to figure out how to
implement this because of this case what
happens if the inner function survives
the invocation of the outer function for
example if the outer function returns
the inner function the inner function
wants to have access to a but a
disappears when when the green function
returns it turned out that the solution
to that was trivial we just allocate
everything on on a heap instead of on a
stack and let the garbage collector
clean it all up and so that's what
JavaScript does so having this this is
how I recommend making objects in
JavaScript from now on so I've got a
constructor function which will take a
specification object we could take
individual parameters but I'd like
having them all in one object that means
we can use an object literal and that
allows the arguments to come in any
order and if there any that we don't
need we can simply ignore them and if
there are any that are missing we can
easily provide defaults I once wrote a
constructor which had ten arguments and
it was really hard to use because nobody
could remember what order they were in
and after a while we discovered that
nobody ever used the third parameter but
we couldn't take it out because all the
programs if I instead had a
specification object then we could have
gotten rid of that parameter and it
would have been easy and the
specification object could also be a
JSON payload right we could get
something over the network which tells
us constitute an object with these
properties and it'll make it for us so I
will initialize member variables
from the specification object and then I
can call other constructors and take the
functions that they return and copy them
into my own other variables so these are
the other methods that are going to be
available to us and then I create my own
methods and because of closure my own
methods will have access to all the
member variables all the other methods
all of our other methods and the
specification object and we don't use
this and then I list all of the methods
that need to be public and I export them
in and I freeze the object freezing is
really important here because it allows
us to have a high integrity object it
cannot be confused or corrupted the only
way to get access to the member data is
through the methods that gives us highly
reliable objects it's the only way to
get highly reliable objects in this
silly language so this is the way that I
recommend that we be making objects in
the future we don't need this so thank
you and good night
[Applause]
as a thank you for your speech I have
one question about webassembly what do
you think about webassembly
where are you I died oh there you are
most so the thing that the the only
benefit that I see from webassembly is
that some things will go faster and most
things will not go faster because
they're already fast enough so if you
have something that really has to go
really fast in a browser then I guess
it's a good idea but it comes at a
significant cost in other ways and for
most applications I think it's just a
distraction thank you thanks for your
speech it was really amazing I have a
question and both of your talks you
mentioned that generators are not as
good as you might think a lot of users
might think but you didn't mention
actually the reason because like for my
opinion and not only for my opinion it
represented illustrate how our minds
work because our minds doesn't work in
in terms of a synchronously like it's
streamlined instruction so do that then
do that and etc etc so actually Kyle
Simpson in the offer of you don't know
Jess
Sirius also mentioned that it's really
really good feature of year six so I'd
like to know in curious about why do you
think that it's not as good as we might
think first off it's unnecessary in
anything which is unnecessary I think we
should get rid of it because I think a
smaller language is better than a bigger
one but it makes control flow much more
complex it breaks some things that used
to be invariance in the language because
things can go in and out even being
weird State the syntax is really ugly it
looks like it's going to return a
function and it's not returning a
function so it's deceptive and confusing
and it's unnecessary I don't see any
value in it at all and and your argument
about it's the way we think that's the
thing we need to change that we're
talking about a paradigm shift right so
granted the other side of the paradigm
shift will take some hours of experience
but once you've accomplished that then
you'll see that the how we're used to
thinking about things argument is
holding us back it's not helping us go
forward so if you were creating a new
language you would leave only
higher-order functions as a way to
handle a synchrony world in in
JavaScript or whatever language yeah
so it's only only thing at the feature
we need to to use to handle all us in 20
world right yeah okay thank you
thank you very much first of all for
trolling he has six glasses users but I
haven't yet still what's wrong with the
arrow functions I thought I explained it
they are visually confusing they don't
look like functions they look like
conditions or relations and there is
that syntactic error that they cannot
return objects or it looks like a valid
thing which might not produce a syntax
error but doesn't mean anything like
what you think it means so the the
saving of writing a keyword I don't
think is worth the cost the other
benefit that you get is that the binding
of this is better but I recommend not
using this anyway so there's no
advantage to that thank you
I actually have two questions but they
really short you mentioned about jslint
so I will be interesting what do you
think about prettier which is like it
forces you to write in a certain style
that not everyone might like and it's
hardly configurable but it makes at
least code consistent and second thing
you mentioned about like trying to make
less errors in your code do you think
typescript can be a solution to that or
at least to like what do you think about
introducing types in JavaScript now
typescript is not a solution to that so
the theory about types and it's an
interesting theory is that types allow
the compiler to find a large class of
errors at compile time which is great
but you don't actually get much benefit
from them because you still have to test
right there's no type system which is so
good which you know you don't have to
test anymore because the type system is
taking care of it that's not the case
you still have to test and it turns out
the sorts of bugs of the type system can
find your tests fine instantly so the
bugs that are found are the lowest value
bugs the bugs that keep you up at night
the type system does not help with those
and actually helps to cause those that
the type system doesn't want to write
some kinds of programs that you need to
write and so you have to circumvent the
type system or you have to turn it off
by casting or some other mechanism so
when we account for it
we tend to give the type system the
value of all of the bugs that it found
but we don't subtract the value of the
bugs that it missed and we don't
consider the value of the bugs that it
caused and I think when you take a full
accounting of types that they're just
not worth it
Sonic's a lot yeah thank you
[Applause]