oh hello to everyone today we we start
with a some more hi some harder material
with respect to the other lectures which
were giving an overview of empirical
studies in software engineering now we
start with with one of the strategies
that that we listed last time and these
controlled experiments here I put a
couple of references that you can take
for to extend some to extend the
material that you will find we will find
in these slides we will go through
through this topic in this lecture and
in a key in the next in the next lecture
in which I will show you guidelines on
how to select to select empirical tests
for controlled experiments so last time
to take take a bit from last lecture we
will show the different types of
research strategies and we saw that
experiments laboratory experiments
controlled experiments in vitro
experiment as a paradigm are typically
strategies that require are contrived
settings so an artificial settings okay
not the natural one a setting in which I
am for example in the lab of course for
software engineering experiment it
doesn't necessarily need to be like a
scientific lab but at least room or a
space in which you can you can eliminate
some confounding factors or some
confounding variables as as we will see
in the next slide so the goal when do
you use a controlled experiment when
your goal is to measure the behavior in
a precise way the behavior of whom may
be very behavior of actors actors can be
as we as we said last time both software
engineers but also tools okay
precision is the core and it is also
important to highlight that these
behavior needs to be related to quite
clearly
identifiable variables so if if the
variables that you want to measure are
too complex and are affected by several
factors in practice it is very unlikely
that you will use an experiment it's
more appropriate to use a field study
okay when you can isolate your variable
and we will see some examples it is
appropriate to use an experiment as a
research strategy okay
control that we speak about controlled
experiments but you will find also
synonyms in the literature so laboratory
experiments but also simply experiment
okay but they refer mostly to the same
thing we will discuss next time a little
bit about the concept of quasi
experiments but we are speaking about
the same practical cases okay let's
start with some practical typical
examples that that can give us an
overview of what we will be speaking
about in this lecture experiments they
can be in software engineering at least
like because experiments of course we
study them in this in this specific in
this specific field they can be with
soft subject or with human subjects so
for example experiment with only
software subject arla like the one that
is that is described here I have two
tools so one tool a and one tool B and
they they do automatic testing okay
they're push-button tools for testing so
I have some code I press a button and
the to test my code and I want to
compare them I want to compare them in
terms of different aspects for example
how many bugs do they find and how how
fast they are in finding this box etc so
I need to compare two tools in this case
since they are push button tools out of
my completely out of fully automatic
tools I don't I do not need to involve
people okay
so it's an experiment with only software
subjects when I have to involves human
subjects it is the case for exam on the
human subject so no software subjects
involved but still in the field of
software engineering there is the second
example so I have a certain method that
is a man was strategy for finding bugs
in the code so I review manually
reviewed the code and I search for bugs
according I don't know according to a
certain checklist for example a new
checklist for finding bugs were also
other defects in the code my question
can be how effective is this guideline
Dizz checklist for experts and how
effective is it for novices ok what is
the differences between novices and
experts in adopting this type of method
so here I'm involving human subjects
I'm studying constructs related to to
the subjects because D is the level of
expertise here that are studying
actually and I want to see how the the
certain strategy how the how the
behavior of the people berries when
using these specific strategies ok
specific strategy varies in terms of
effectiveness
so this effectiveness can can be again
defined in different ways so how many
bugs do they find out how quick are them
in finding bugs so but the idea here is
that while in the first example you have
only softer subjects in here you have
only human subjects and strategy ok but
most of the time you mix it of course
you have both softer subjects and human
subjects because out of my fully
automatic tools rarely exists in
software engineering so it is more
likely that you have an interactive tool
for testing and you want to see if it is
more appropriate for novices or experts
okay
like the example before in which you
have a method but in case you have a
softer too okay but you can have also
other more complex cases so you have two
tools
1 both interactive and you want to
compare them so in this case you do you
don't care about the level of experience
so now this is an expert you just want
to compare them but you need to involve
people because they are interactive
tools for testing ok and in this case
how will you select these people hey I
will select them if I if I assume that
these tools are somewhat independent on
the expertise of the people I need to
involve people with various expertise
and within a balanced and general way so
that my sample of people is somehow
representative of the typical people
typical population of developers so that
somehow I eliminate I get rid of the
expertise aspects in this experience in
this expert in this specific experiment
and I just compared to lay and tool be
like they were automated - ok although
they are interactive ok this is the
general idea for this type of
experiments we will see more in in
detail this type of little little tricky
aspects when we will see more detailed
examples you can have also other other
cases again you have inter - interactive
tools and in this case you want to see
which one is more appropriate for
novices and which one is more
appropriate for experts okay so
expertise now becomes again a relevant
aspect to consider or you can even
compare tools and approaches so for
example in a company I may use a typical
code review strategy with a certain
checklist and I want to introduce a
certain tool a ok I am comparing a tool
and a method and I want to see which one
is better
again this is an experiment that
involves software subjects so the tool
but involve also involves human subject
because I need to recruit people that
use the actually use these approaches ok
of course things become tricky
if the tool is a fully automatic and the
method of course requires some manual
intervention so you need to you need to
really take care you need to carefully
consider the variable that you are
evaluating in this case but let's let's
these are these are examples and - now
let's see how this experiments are
placed in our in our diagram of theory
building in software engineering and in
in science in general basically
controlled experiments are positioned
our deductive approaches so are
positioned in the top-down direction of
this diagram so they are not using
induction but they're using the duction
I have a certain theory ok a certain
theory taken from the literature or
observed from previous more exploratory
study and I formalized some hypothesis
from this theory and then what I want to
do is to test the hypotheses so in this
lecture you will see how to how to
approach this all deductive process ok
that that we saw last time in the
context of theory building with
induction abduction and adduction ok
what is the process for controlled
experiments and at the end of this of
these two lectures you will I will show
you more in detail what they all these
blocks mean but the idea is that taken
from the from the previous slide in
which you start from some theory and you
go down towards the observation of
reality here the situation is similar so
you start from the theory you build some
research question in the way that I
explained last time you create
hypotheses in variable definitions so
you operationalize the constructs of the
theory through variables as you remember
the terminology that we used to
and tip we do our research design that
means also selecting the type of
selecting the type of how many groups
for example of people do I want to
involve and how to map these variables
into actual data that I can gather okay
and in the research design I also define
the measures for the different variables
then I recruit the participants and I
select test artifacts for my experiments
collect data analyze the data it is the
execution of this paramount and then I
discussed several validity threats that
are all related to different layers to
different levels of my study I report my
answers to the research question and
finally I discuss how the theory changed
based on my experiment so I start from a
theory and I perform this study so I go
top-down towards reality I test the
theory really test in a quantitative way
and then I discuss if the theory is
confirmed in which way it is in which
way my my scope of validity is extended
for a certain theory with respect to
previously existing studies and and so
basically discussing in the end means
comparing with existing work in the
field and explaining in which way your
experiments are advanced their knowledge
in the specific field ok this is just to
give you an overview of what controlled
experiments are and how are they
positioned in the in the process of
building theories ok now let's see more
in depth what are the elements that you
will learn in this latch ok here you
will see a lot of words that you
probably do not know and they are the
core elements of all the approach of the
controlled experiment approach then
going to explain so one fundamental
element this this picture you you have
to read it starting from design collect
data and afterwards analyzed it okay you
start from a certain hypothesis that is
the right from the theory if you
remember if you remember we had
propositions in the theory that can be
translated into some form of hypothesis
we will see examples of abbath disease
later on then you have the concept of
independent variables dependent
variables and control variables this is
the identification the
operationalization of the so called
constructs of the of my theory and i
have different so-called treatments okay
we will see what are the treatments in
the in very few slides okay so basically
this is the design that is somehow
transforming your theory in something
more operational and more controllable
okay then you do you collect the data so
you measure this variable that you have
define and you have all your data from
the experiment so the experiment takes
place after you designed it takes place
and afterwards you have a lot of data
and you have to analyze them so in the
rest of the picture you have all the
concepts that are needed to analyze the
data in controlled experiments analyze
the data most of the time means doing
hypothesis testing
so quantitative test of the hypotheses
according to some statistical test you
take what is it it's a statistical test
for you it is generally a black box in
which you insert a certain significant
value a value that indicates how sure
you want to be of your results basically
and outputs to three main values the two
main values and another value can be
computed later on but two main value one
is the test statistic that is a
numerical value that doesn't mean so
much in itself but is the main output
let's say of the test we will see the
meaning the specific meaning later on
the end the p-value the pivot
value is a value that while significant
tells you how sure you want to be about
about the results of your test the
p-value indicates basically how sure can
you be about the value of the test once
this has been performed understanding
this concept of significance and p-value
will be it will be not straightforward
but I will do my best to to show you
pictures and some graphical diagrams to
allow you to to understand them at best
another thing that you can extract from
these analysis analyzed data is the
effect size so for example the test can
tell you how significant is your is your
results so how sure can you be that that
that your test is successful so how sure
can you do for example that in this case
normally that your null hypothesis is
rejected but this we will see later on
but how sure can you be of the
conclusion of this test and the effect
size is how much is this effect that are
measuring with my test big large okay so
one is their p-value out was telling you
how much can you be confident let's say
how significant is your result and the
emphasize tells you how much how large
is the effect is the effect that you
have observed in your data okay after
this analysis you have a say you have
more confidence about the reliability of
your hypothesis so actually we are never
speaking about accepting and hypothesis
but we are speaking about rejecting a
null hypothesis and we will see this in
the next slide some explanation some
explanation about that but the idea here
that you need to remember is that you
start with up with a hypothesis that you
don't know whether it's true or not and
at the end
the data analysis you may have come to
ERISA that tells you these hypothesis is
more likely to be true than to be false
okay
the left part will require your
creativity so designing and also
collecting data somehow because it
involves selecting also the people the
people involved in the experiment
because most of the time you will deal
with human and software all together
requires your creativity you have to
invent how to pass from your research
question to variables and you need to
justify the measures that you are using
for the different variables okay and
this second part is mostly automated as
I said the test for you as a software
engineer will be mostly a back black box
but you need to understand what are this
concepts and how to interpret them
because there is some statistics in them
and it is not fully straightforward okay
so let's see more in detail what are
this controlled experiment with some
definition now we've seen a bit of a
high level high level view of what are
the different elements that you will
encounter through these lectures but is
not now let's see let's see more formal
let's say definitions okay a controlled
experiments let's let's read the slide
is an environmental investigation of a
testable hypothesis in which conditions
are set up to isolate the variables of
interest that are independent variables
and tests how they affect certain
measurable outcomes the dependent
variables so what does it mean look at
the picture and I think is quite
intuitive you have some input variable
okay some input variable that you want
to change and these are the independent
variables okay
the experiment is this box okay the
treatments box let's call it and you
want to see how certain the
variables so variables of output in this
box vary based on the independent one
okay the treatment what is a treatment
treatment is a combination of values for
the independent variables what does it
mean in an example can can clarify
everything here for example in the in
the in the case of the experiment with
software tools I may have the
independent variable is the test into
the testing to does that I'm using okay
the treatments is one treatment is with
tool a and the second treatment is which
will be because the testing tool as a
variable can take tool a or tool B as
values okay so I have two different two
different treatments and the dependent
variable is the thing that I want to
measure for example can for example can
be the number of bugs found in the
software or the speed okay this is a
this is the basic element of any
experiment so independent variables that
are also sometimes called factors okay
the treatments that are combinations of
values of the independent variable and
the dependent variable so the measurable
outcome that I want to observe so I
changed something and I want to observe
something as output it is important to
consider this these are this other part
what I want to do is to isolate the
independent variable because I want to
see just the effect on them of them on
the dependent variables okay so this
means that in the Oh experimental all
the treatment all the other variables
need to be controlled okay so in the
example of the testing tool what I need
to do is that the what can be the other
variables that can affect my dependent
ones okay what can be the
other aspects the other factors that
combined with the choice of the testing
tool can modify the number of bugs found
well obviously the type of code that I'm
using for testing okay the code sample
that I'm using for testing if this code
samples need to be need to be to have a
sufficient variation of number of bugs
so that I can see so that they are
sufficiently representative of typical
code base okay so I need to control the
variable of number of bugs in code but I
have also a number of bad like not
number of bugs found in terms of
dependent variables but number of bugs
included in the code that I'm that I'm
considering in the experiment included
in the console but also the length of
this code sample because in reality I
can have different lengths and this may
affect for example the speed of the tool
or actually the number of bugs that a
certain tool is able to find okay so
this is this is to tell you that here in
an email like in any controlled
experiment the independent variables
need to be isolated if I want to say
that the variation on the dependent
variable is due to the modification of
the independent one otherwise if I don't
control these variables what happens it
happens that I may observe variation in
the dependent variable but this may be
caused not by the independent one but by
the other variables that I didn't
control so it's like being somewhat in a
in a field study where I take things
from reality
I don't isolate elements and I see their
collective impact on a certain variables
but of course the validity of what I am
finding and the connection between
independent in the independent variable
is much weaker okay so it is really
important to to remember to remember
this when you design an expense
so again this is alighting a little bit
more what we mean by controlled variable
here for example I was recent the sample
length the type of language also because
some - maybe maybe working in only on a
certain language the degree of
complexity under of the code because
also this may impact on the ability of
the tool to to find bugs so all this
variable need to be controlled they can
be related to two objects like in this
case in this case they are related to
the different to the different code
samples that I'm using in the test in
the experiment and they can also be
related to human subjects in this
example I'm using software subjects only
but if humans are involved as I as I
briefly touched before you will need
some representatives of different types
of developers with different expertise
for example if I want to make this
experiment independent of the expertise
of the people so I need to control the
expertise variable okay what are the
main characteristics that the control
variables should have and at least the
the sample that I'm including in this
experiment should have there should be
equivalent for each treatment so not
equal but least equivalent they can be
there should be general enough so to
cover with my experiment the the largest
part of my scope of interest and
homogeneous they need to be homogeneous
of course is another way of seeing of
saying it is a way of saying that they
are not emphasizing any any aspect if
your if you are using for example a code
sample you cannot have all all the code
all the C code of a certain length and
all the Java code shorter okay you need
to have some some homogeneous
representation
datian of all the different factors in
the sample that you consider and
representative okay they need to
represent some reality okay they need to
be representative or some population of
code in this case okay so it's very
difficult to do this to do this election
and you need to justify your selection
and very often if the control variables
are many you end up dealing with the
needs to constrain some some dimension
we will see an example later on so when
when I consider you might subject as a
simplified before the control variable
may be related to the experience of
developers for examples or age or like
gender or like if you are using
biometric sensor also the the color of
the skin may may affect that so there
there are several there are several
several aspects that that may be
considered to have to control your
variables okay so let's go to some more
formal definitions okay youyou have now
a general understanding of what we are
speaking about here but now we give some
some definition and I will generally
read what's written here so we start
with the definition of hypothesis where
what is it is the statement that I want
to test with my experiment so as I shown
as I've shown I start with the
hypothesis and at the end of hypothesis
at the end of the hmm at the end of my
experiment I have either rejected my it
said I have either rejected a certain
hypothesis or I have some support for
that type of disease okay the apology's
normally derived from a research
question for example what is the
difference between a and B in terms of
bug detection capability the same
example as before so is it better
a or B for for finding bugs in this code
okay
I then include the hypothesis include
variables that represent my contracts
the costs of interest that may be tools
methods actor number of bugs so all the
things that may be involved in the in
the experiments and that are relevant
for me and the process is normally
concerned the measurable impact that a
certain variation or some construct can
have on other constructs variation in
input variable can have on output
variable so variation of independent
variables can have on dependent variable
so to a finds more bugs than to be or to
a finds less or equal box than to be
okay these are examples of hypotheses
that are derived from the research
question and that are concerned with the
specific construct in in my in my my
experiments in my in my scope or in my
scope of interest okay and when when we
do is a potus's testing we normally have
a null and alternative hypothesis okay
then the null hypothesis is the one that
I will test okay but the one that I am
trusted in is the alternative one okay
this is a tricky tricky thing that you
at this moment you will have to take as
a fact okay when you do a part of this
testing you're actually testing a null
hypothesis the null hypothesis that is
telling you the exact opposite of what
you want to to show but it will become a
little clearer later on okay at the
moment you just take it as a as a as an
assumption okay so more definitions
again you already understood what our
independent dependent variable treatment
and controlled variables but here you
have precise definition so independent
variables are operationalization or
constructs that i want to isolate
whose values I want to manipulate with
the example you see this is clear I work
to isolate the type of tool so that I
want to see just the influence of tool
or I want to isolate the expertise of
actors so that I just I just took I just
consider that and I want to manipulate
because I do different treatment because
I assign different values to these
independent variables then I have
treatments that are actually
combinations of values for the
independent variables so here I have if
I have to lay and tool B and I test them
and I compare them I have one variable
the type of tool and two treatments okay
I normally speak about one factor two
treatments or one variable two
treatments is equivalent okay but in the
books you always find one factor okay
after you find quite frequently one
factor two treatments okay but don't get
confused with with this it's just
synonyms okay or you can have if you
want to to consider also the expertise
as as a variable you will have four
treatments because you have you need to
you need to experiment with to lay an
expert to lay a novices to be an expert
to be a novices so you have two
variables and four treatments so you see
that it's easily edited your design can
easily get complicated because when when
you have just the tools and one variable
you just run the experiments and you
compare between two elements in here you
just added one variable that is the
expertise but you involve people you
need to so you need more effort and in
addition you have four treatments so you
need unity enough people also to carry
out this experiment in four different
groups one group using to lay one group
one group of experts schools using to
lay one group of experts in to be etc
okay dependent variables dependent
variables are the output and they are
operationalization of constructs that
want to measure based on the
manipulation of the independent
variables okay so these are the constant
the operationalization of those
constructs that vary based on the
independent variables okay for example
the number of box and finally controlled
variable we discuss them extensively and
these are again operationalization of
course but in practice they are
attributes of human subjects or objects
as we saw before definite to control to
mask or prevent their impact on the
dependent variable this controlled
variable I need to control them because
otherwise the variation of the dependent
variable is not linked only to the
variation of the independent one but may
be caused by the control by this other
variable okay and for example as it was
exemplified multiple time I have to test
on some code that is sufficiently
general and equivalent for all cases
let's see an example you've seen these
examples on what hidden in the in the
previous explanation but now let let us
see it more extensively so this is
example is an example of an experiment
of the experiment with just software
okay my goal is to understand which tool
is better for testing among two
available choices a and B okay these are
push button tools so I don't need to
consider the impact of the human in
using this tool okay the independent
variable we already saw it is the tool
is one part okay the treatments are also
straightforward so I have to lay and
should be one factor to treatment what
is the dependent variable
well my objective is to see which one is
better what do I mean by better okay
better is a quite vague concept is it
better in terms of speed where
in terms of bugs found I want to
consider both aspects so I in this case
I will have two dependent variable and I
define them as effectiveness and
efficiency so I compared the two tool in
terms of effectiveness that is how many
bugs do they found compared with the
total number of bugs that is present in
the culture because in this case I
assume that the two could not be able to
find some specific types of bugs and
efficiency that is related to the
running time and I define it as the
running time in relation to the number
of bugs that are found okay
or I could define it also in relation to
the length of the code this is just what
I decided I decided this these
quantities to me okay I decide what I'm
interested okay in this case I have two
these two dependent variable one
dependent variable and two treatments
okay now comes the difficult part I have
to identify the control variables what
and the question that I need to answer
is what can impact on effectiveness and
efficiency beside the type of tool well
the user well the user we said no it
does an impact because the tool is just
a push button to is fully automatic the
language of the code yes then probably
is it is too hard to consider all the
type of codes because it would need a
too large sample and in addition one of
the tool is able to test just for C so I
want to focus just on C code so you see
that I'm reducing my my scope of
interest somehow
before I was speaking about difference
between today and should be in finding
bugs but now I am saying that I am
focusing just on C code on a certain
type of language of course also another
variable to take into account is the
chosen code but the code shows and code
samples as we exemplified before so but
which are the attributes of the chosen
code that my
impact on the on the dependent variables
where might be the actual number of bugs
in the code model so I need some
sufficient very a sufficient variation
in terms of number of bugs in each
module that I'm testing the length of
the module as I said before the some
tool might be more effective if it's
working in shorter in shorter code so I
need two quite different and realistic
representation of different codes the
complexity of the of the code another
variable and the domain of the code why
because maybe depending on the domain I
a certain type of solutions that are
always adopted in a certain code and a
certain tool is more appropriate for the
features that the code in that domain
shows for example in a safety critical
environment I may not be allowed to use
global variables or I may not be allowed
to use pointers okay so a certain tool
may be more effective for the specific
quality specific feature of the safety
critical sector of the railway sector
for example while it may not work
properly if the C code is pointers and
has other characteristics of course you
can you can frame it in in different
ways you can look at at the different
and the different characteristics that
of the code or you can just say ok this
code is coming from a database of
railway code and this code is coming
from a database of I don't know
financial financial software okay so
these are all variables that you need to
take into account and justify when you
design your experiment ok so as I said I
have to create a code sample that has
sufficient variations
you know these variables and if I can do
very eight certain variable if I cannot
have a sufficient variation in a certain
variable I have to fix it like I did
with the C code or like I'm made to need
to do for the domain
okay and I need to make this choice
explicit as Italy mists my scope of
interest okay or in this case if the
theory independent it may limit your
scope or validity as well but in this
case you can say okay my theory I want
to refocus my theory only on this domain
and on this type of God okay
so this creates a boundary so the
controlled variable somewhat create a
boundary in your scope of interest okay
this is another example with software
and new months okay
and in this case like it is an example
that we considered also before I want to
see if the experience of the user
affects the effectiveness of a certain
tool okay the dependent variable in this
case is there is the one that we took
from last experiment so it's
defectiveness that is the number of bugs
found divided by the total number of
bugs in a certain piece of code so this
is the dependent variable that I want to
that I want to observe while they're
independent variable is is the
experience of the of the user but the
issue here is how can I measure this
experience while before the independent
variable was tool a or told B it was it
was quite clear straightforward we
didn't even think about measuring the
independent variable because it was a
binary variable basically so either you
use tool a or to B but in this case your
independent variable is the experience
and this is how to measure it I can
consider how can I measure the
experience of a user where I can
consider the years of experience is stay
in testing or I can ask what the years
of experience may tell you something but
they don't tell you how much how expert
is really that person so you may want to
ask the colleagues to judge a certain
person and to score this person
for for expertise in testing okay um so
in general it is better to select one
independent measure for the variable
okay so otherwise have many too many
treatments and might not find enough
participants
okay so better to select one of this
measure and justify but okay so let's
consider since it is easier to evaluate
although not necessarily perfect
I consider the years but sure that you
consider one year two years four years
five years so by single year or can I
can I group this year well if I decide
that I choose one two three four as
differences so I want to see how a
different of one year only can affect
the usage of a certain tool well this
may be difficult in several terms
because maybe the difference between two
and three years of experience is not
that much and in addition I need to find
enough people for the experiment so I
have to find many people who have just
one year many people who have just two
years many people who have three years
and so it may be very complicated again
as an experiment so probably is better
to separate to select some levels okay
how to select the level I have to do
some assumptions okay I have to take
some assumption take from the literature
or justify and defend my decision okay
there is no no silver bullet in here
okay and often you resort on other
studies that have done choice that is
similar to yours or you you have to
consider also common sense and your
knowledge for example I can decide for
two levels okay and in this level I have
two treatments one from zero to one
years novices and more than five years
experts okay so in this case I have
eliminated people that are in the
in-between ok there is a radical
difference of course between zero
- one year and more than five years okay
so this is evident and it is common
sense that I don't need to just justify
much okay so think about that of course
if you have people that have between two
and four years of experience and these
are a candidate for your experiment you
cannot use them you cannot see really
you cannot involve them okay
now it will identify the control
variables again the question is the
usual one what can impact on my outcomes
besides the experience here I don't have
the code I don't have the objects but I
have people so in this case I can have
age gender demographic variable so how
old am where do they come from where did
they study okay from which company are
they coming from and of course again the
code on which the tool is is applied
okay so the other previous variable so
you see that this experiment becomes
much more complicated I have to make
some choice I fix some some code base we
use the same for a subject and make sure
also in this case in say up also
interacting aspects make sure none of
them have shown I've seen the code in
advance because if for example if I have
to test certain code that I have already
tested I know already which are the bugs
so it's this is a this is affecting my
experiment so and but all but since in
some cases it may be the case that if
you if you're using code from a certain
company and the people are from the same
company it is possible that P those
people have seen that code okay and
these joopa dyes your experiments okay
and and then I control demographic
variables okay
select the rebels in a way that I have a
representative group of people without
imbalance in terms of age for example
otherwise if I cannot do that again I
restrict my scope of interest if I find
just people for example you know that
are all coming from the same company of
course the result of my experiment is
limited to the characteristic of the
specific company and may be extended to
companies with similar characteristics
and with similar trainings for example
ok so at the end this is my design and I
have a group with a comparable
experience novice or expert but
variations in terms of age gender and
other demographic aspects and I have a
code base so I have designed my
experience you see that here when I said
this requires a lot of creativity it
requires a lot of creativity you have to
think truly about what are your
constructs how to measure them how to
create your variables how to how to
measure the variables and you have to
consider different factors that are also
related to the possibilities that you
have because when you build a software
experiment a software engineering
experiment you you don't have infinite
resources if you had used it for example
if we are involved in developers and as
we said in the last lecture this
developer they have to do their work
their daily work so they cannot stay in
your experiment for two hours and there
are also fatigue and other factors that
may affect the experiment so is the is
really again optimizing between
different factors okay so what are the
pros and cons of controlled experiment
the main Pro the main the main advantage
physical experiment is that you're using
you are doing really real science ok
with the numbers because controlled
experiments are quantitative but up to
now you've never you didn't see any
number ok I didn't see any number so you
see that they are real science with
numbers real science means also dealing
a lot with the creativity with
creating this constrained environment of
the lab experiments of the control the
spam okay and the great advantage is
also that they can be applied to
identifies identify cause effect
relationship for specific well defined
variables why as we said before the goal
of the experiment is is to isolate the
independent variable and control the
other one so that the dependent variable
is just dependent on variations
variations of the independent one okay
so this allows me to say when I change
this I have a change in that and this
change is not caused by anything else
okay
disadvantage there are many okay they
are applicable only to well-defined
problem in which you can actually define
and isolate these variables as I said at
the beginning if you have cases in which
it is very complicated to to isolate the
variable of interest because the
contextual factors that may affect them
are many and cannot be cannot be
separated by by the measurement of the
variable it is very hard to perform an
experiment and they are hard
also if you cannot simulate the right
conditions in the rod so if the control
confounding factors confounding
variables may be too r2 to control so
the other variable that may impact the
dependent variable and the other issues
that the experiment is not realistic
they behavior especially the behaviorist
people of people in a in an experimental
environment is very different from from
their behavior in the in the real world
of software development but the the
obvious thing is that while in a lab the
experiment is carried out and in trust
maybe one hour two hour maximum also
because afterwards people get tired in
software development you have eight
hours of programming in a day or even
more and in addition
our dealing with the dynamic and
ever-changing context with several
people coming to the developers of
emails coming requests coming randomly
so it is a much more complex reality
that changes the behavior of the
developer and that influences the
behavior of the developer and of course
recreating this complexity in the lab is
not possible even just for the matter of
time okay
another issue is that if you do an
experiment with software with human
subject is desire to recruit the
subjects of course as I said develop
yourself to develop and many managers
need to manage so people have to work ok
and recruiting people for example with
expertise higher than 5 5 years it is
complicated ok and very often in
controlled experiment in software
engineering students are used ok
other PhD students or or master students
ok
they are proxies of develop or
real-world developers but of course in
practice they can rarely mimic the
degree of expertise ok
they are used as proxies when you want
to test for example a new methodology or
a new tool that you that you are
proposing for software engineer what
software engineers but they use it and
they are used because it's easier to
involve students and it it is less
costly to recruit them because you may
pay them a little manual or a little
reward
I think that is always important to give
in an experiment you always have to
think hey but this person why is she or
he coming to the experiments either for
learning something either because this
person is forced but you don't want that
of course and or because you give them a
kind of soft reward or because they
learn something from from the experience
ok
so you have to clean it to carefully
consider this when designing the
experiment thinking about recruiting as
we saw in the in our example the design
is time consuming we spent a lot of time
thinking about the experiments and can
get very complicated very easily okay so
if the core the thing becomes too
complicated the actual control becomes
difficult okay
so better the recommendation she is that
better to keep your experiments simple
okay otherwise your control experiment
frequently risks to go out of control
okay so now we pass two hypothesis
testing but now first let's let's make
let's make a little break okay