so let's start the second part about hypothesis testing
so now we have seen
all the principles related to concepts
such as dependent independent variable
controlled variable treatments etc and
now let's go into the tool that allows
us to to confirm or to support let's say
my theory or to identify whether the
evidence that I can gather for the
experiment is sufficient to support it
in this this is a lesson with a lot of
statistics so I will provide you the
information that is useful to understand
the main principle but to really
understand the things you need really
need to resort to other two other
resources so to use other books for
example the book that I suggested and
other other links that I will point
throughout the lecture I will use
sometimes where a few timers actually
the word magic when something needs to
be assumed so I will not explain in
depth some aspects and I will I will
give them as to you as information if
you are interested you can you can do
additional research by yourself
but so that it is clear I do this so
that it is clear that it is not that you
didn't understand something but it's
just given you as an assumption okay so
let's start with some detailed
definition of what our hypothesis is
let's read the slide a hypothesis is a
statistical testable statement derived
from a theory and in practice from a
research question so I have my theory I
write down my research question in the
way that I explained during the first
lecture and is a statistical
statistically testable statement we will
see through this lecture what this
really mean a hypothesis is a predictive
statement concerning the impact of some
independent variable on some dependent
we've already understood now what is an
independent viable independent bible
hypothesis is a predictive statement so
every time I change in some way the
independent variable I expect to have
some effect some predictable effect on
the dependent variable this is a core
point when we do i potter this testing
our goal is to refute the negation of
the theory the reason for this you will
understand it throughout this lecture
but for now let's take it as as a fact
okay normally whenever we do i potter
this testing we start from the theory
and the first thing that we do is
Express the so-called null hypothesis h0
this hypothesis is the negation of the
statements that i want to support on the
predictive statement that i want support
so simply simply the theory does not
apply this is the typical null
hypothesis it is expressed normally like
the as a statement like the one written
here there is no effort between the
independent variable and the dependent
variable so the the changes in the
independent variable do not affect the
dependent variable and these null
hypothesis is assumed to be true unless
there is evidence from my data from the
data of my experiments that allows me to
reject the null hypothesis and the
statistical test is actually oriented to
allow you to reject the null hypothesis
of course you have to express both the
null hypothesis as I explained now and
also there are tentative hypotheses
which is the thing that you want to
support the alternative hypothesis says
the theory predicts of course if h0 is
rejected so if the null hypothesis is
false there is an evidence that h1 can
be correct so can be supported so the
alternative hypothesis may be true
this is an example so let's go directly
to an example here I have a method M or
a tool T for finding bugs a method or a
tool doesn't doesn't change anything so
something that I want that I want to use
to support my strategy for finding bugs
and the null hypothesis is this one the
experience of the developer does not
have that the average time to find bugs
in this case I imagined to have two
groups so novices and Express so people
with different groups with different
experience like in the example that we
discussed in the previous part of the
lecture and this is expressed according
to this this is a null hypothesis is
expressed with this formula so the devil
each time for now this is is equal to
over the average time of experts so
there is no difference what I want to
show actually is that the experience of
the developer actually affects the
average time to find bugs so my
alternative hypothesis is the one that
you see in this slide so the average
time of the analysis is different from
the average time of experts in this case
we will speak about two-tailed
hypothesis to be tested and you will
understand why we use this name in the
next slide so for now just start start
getting some confidence with this type
of terminology so we are speaking about
two-tailed hypothesis here when you have
a name and you another hypothesis that
is speaking about no effect okay another
example let's see now because in this
case I'm showing I'm looking at
differences so there may be the case
that the average time of novices is
higher than the average time of expert
or lower than the average time of
experts if I want to know something more
a little more so if I want to know who
is quicker between novices and expert
I need to modify my hypothesis I need to
formulate it in a different way the
experiment is exactly the same so I am I
to group
metal groups one of novices and one of
experts but the formulation of the null
hypothesis is different how is it the
average time to find bugs of novices is
less than or equal to the one of experts
so is expressed in this way so this is
what I want to reject that I want to
reject the fact that novices are faster
than experts and of course the other way
around for the alternative hypothesis is
the average time to find bugs or novices
is greater than the one of experts this
is what I want to show when you have
these inequalities we speak about one
tael hypothesis to be tested so when you
have the equivalence you speak about to
say their position here you speak about
one tail about this again this will be a
clearly explained later on so let's
introduce this other concept these other
ingredients disagree that is one of the
core ingredients of how hypothesis
testing which is the test statistic
during that process is test normally I
perform my experiment and I take a
sample of data and I usually compare
them into a single value this single
value is called test statistic okay so
imagine you have collected your data and
this data can be combined and give you
just one single number is just a number
this number is crucial because it can
tell you whether you can reject the null
hypothesis or not the value of the test
statistic the way you compute this test
statistic depends on several factors
that are related basically to the
experiments that you that you have to
carry out and basically the way of
computing this test statistic is
deterministic and is given you by
statisticians okay so in this case I
didn't write magic but the way of
computing the Resta T stood for you at
the moment is magic so let's see here an
example here I have my testers on
I my blue box my test is the so called
unpaired t-test this is a specific test
that is suitable for my specific case as
I said the choice is deterministic and
you will understand which specific test
to choose in the follow in the following
lecture you have collected your data so
time of noir physicists and time of
expert for each novice an expert you
input this data into your test box into
your black box and this impair test
which is which impair T test that
basically compared the means of two
independent some posts how to read this
this can be read by looking at my sample
I have a sampled novice is an expert so
and I have so different people so this
sample are independent and I want to see
whether the mean time is different so
you understand why this test allows you
to either reject the null hypothesis or
fail to reject it so we will see better
this terminology later on okay but
imagine you have this black box so with
the test that is called unpaired t-test
you have your input and you produce the
T value that is for example - 0 38 and
this is my test statistic my value okay
so a value that is produced by the test
now let's go to one of the crucial slide
of this presentation we said at the
beginning of the presentation that there
is a my assumption I start off with that
with the assumption that the null
hypothesis is true and I want to reject
the null hypothesis so I want to show
basically this that this assumption is
layer is likely to be false so starting
from this assumption I imagined to have
a population in which the null
hypothesis is actually true and I
imagined to repeat an experiment with
the same design as mine
multiple time in this population so
sampling taking samples from this
population in which the null hypothesis
is true and every time I compute my test
distich according to according to the
type of test that depends on the type of
experiments that have chosen so the same
black box I'm using the black box and
I'm producing this number by repeating
this experiment several time the test
statistic so the value the value that is
produced by the statistical test will
follow a certain distribution which one
also this case the distribution is magic
is given you by statistician and in this
specific case of of the test that I was
considering is the student T
distribution so they are paired t-test
use the student T distribution is just a
name for you you will you will not need
to learn what is it about the idea but
the idea you have to understand it so
you are repeating these experiments and
you count basically the time that your
that your test statistics as a certain
value and you based on the on this
repetition of experiment you draw your
distribution of values you draw your
distribution of value and you have what
it is shown here in the slide you have a
distribution that is centered on the
value that the test statistic s when the
data of my experiment confirms exactly
the null hypothesis my fictional
experiment is of this type okay why
because if in the population the null
hypothesis is true and I repeat the
experiment taking this taking my sample
from the population in the majority of
the cases the T value will be will be
the one associated to the confirmation
of the null hypothesis because the null
hypothesis is true in this population
so that's why the majority of my samples
will have exactly the value exactly the
value that the test statistic has when
the null hypothesis is true so the
central area if the null hypothesis is
true if I do an experiment it is very
unlikely a random experiment an
experiment with a random sample in the
population it is very unlikely that the
test statistic will fall on the tail and
this is the trick this is the idea so it
is very unfrequent that a sample will
fall on the right tail or on the left
tail and actually this is what I I want
to show with my experiment I want to
show that with my experiment that the T
value of my experiment will fall on the
tail we will see we will see better
winner with a slide later on my tester
so my if my test statistic force around
the tails I can reject the null
hypothesis and this is my my objective
this is my goal okay so my goal is I
built after building this frictional
distribution in which the null
hypothesis is true I want to show that
there is a so my experiment so that
isthis is still the test statistic he
would be so rare in a population in
which the null hypothesis is true that
probably the null hypothesis is false
okay let's see little bit a little bit
of remarks so our final goal is to
evaluate whether a test statistic value
obtained from my experiment is so rare
that it justifies rejecting the null
hypothesis for entire population based
on our sample data of course
again I remark I don't know the entire
distribution of my test statistic but
this can be inferred based on the
statistic of the sample data and the
hypothesis I wanted a so it depends
actually on my experiment and there is a
deterministic way for choosing the test
so that's why in this context I will
assume that some magic occurs and I know
that a statistic I know the experiments
they I know the type of tests that I
need to choose critical region so we
said we want our test statistic value to
follow on the tails
this is on the tails of my distribution
this is the other thing that our goal so
before doing the experiment this happens
everything happens before doing my
experiment I set the so-called critical
region the critical region are DRS that
are identified by those stiva those test
statistic value that are acceptable for
me so the ones that belongs to the
tailor so those values that allow me to
reject the null hypothesis so this is
the area that I want to fall to fall on
this is them let's say the segments of t
statistic that that i want to consider
that I consider as acceptable for a
successful experiment for rejecting the
null hypothesis this area indicate the
risk of rejecting the null hypothesis
when true so this area that we will we
will name in a moment in the case the
risk of rejecting the null hypothesis
when true why because it's associated
with a population that is assumed to in
which the null hypothesis is assumed to
be true this area is called significance
level and again indicates the risk of
rejecting the null hypothesis when this
is true it is normally denoted by alpha
you will see this alpha several times
and it normally takes this value 0.01
0.05 0.1 these are typical values for
alpha and I explained I will explain in
a moment why we use this value I want to
select a certain specific value instead
we have another concept that is 1 minus
alpha so the the opposite the opposite
of alpha that is the so-called
confidence level and indicates how
configure want to be about the results
of my test the difficult buy of courses
winos minus 1 minus alpha so 0.99 0.95
etcetera alpha sets the standard for our
extreme the data must be that all my
experiment must be before we
reject the null hypothesis this alpha we
at this moment I didn't do any
experiment okay I didn't I didn't
compute any data from my experiment
afterwards I will complete the data from
my experiment I will obtain the test
statistic value for my experiment and I
will have another value the so called
p-value that I will compare with my
alpha and therefore this p-value will
indicate our extreme the data are and we
will see it in the next in the next
slides
let's see better what is the confidence
level like significance level is this
area in the in the in details the
corresponding confidence level is in the
other region is in the central region
the so called the so called acceptance
region let's see the values so I said
before that the specific value of the
specific values of significance of alpha
they have a meaning and the intuitive
meaning is is listed on the on the last
column so the a said that the
significance level indicates a risk the
risk can be a different level so from
catastrophic to moderate when I set
alpha to 0.001 it means that the risk of
rejecting the null hypothesis when this
is true is catastrophic this from an
intuitive point of view means that I
lose more than a hundred million euros
that may mean large loss of life like a
nuclear disaster or and also without
losing lives a large loss in software
engineering we always saw our most
frequently used this level of
significance so 0.05 that is associated
with a risk level important and
indicates that it
there is no lives lost and there are
some injuries in some cases of course
when when the risk is higher you may
increase your risk level to critical and
choose a significance level that is more
strict but in most of the cases 0.05 is
is the reference this is just to give
you a meaning for for this value that
and let you understand that they are
somewhat established by by the community
you don't need to invent an alpha every
time you do an experiment although you
although when I described how to perform
an experiment I suggest you should
select that so it should select alpha
because you should be aware of this of
this risk level and estimations in
software engineering yeah we normally
use these values let's pass now to type
1 and type 2 errors this is another
concept related to my alpha so my
significance level there are four
possible situation when I perform my
experiment and when after after
designing this this hypothetical series
of experiments in a population which the
null hypothesis is true
I then prefer my experiments and I can
do the different type of error the first
error is the hole type one error and is
the error that corresponds to the case
in which the null hypothesis in the real
population is actually true but I reject
incorrectly so I fall in the area in
their alpha area in the in the rejection
area and the area in the critical region
basically but in practice in the reality
the null hypothesis was true and this
probability is indicated by alpha or
there may be another case in which the
null hypothesis is false but I'm not
able to reject it so I fail to reject
the null hypothesis when this is false
and this is normally indicated by beta
so how to remember this to remember this
you can revert the thing so my
alternative iPod the type 1 error is in
the case that my alternative hypothesis
is wrong so my theory is wrong but I
support it anyway while the type 2 error
is is the case in which my tentative
hypothesis was correct but unfortunately
I rejected it I was not able to I was
not able to show that the null
hypothesis was was false okay
we normally in practice we normally
focus on minimizing type 1 errors so you
will see most of the the information
will be associated that I will give you
in the next slides will be associated
with alpha and because we are mostly
focusing on on cases in which we we want
to have a result that that for which the
risk of incorrectly rejecting the null
hypothesis is lower okay
while beta 4 for us is is a bit less
relevant but we will see the
relationship between between the two
values at the end of the presentation so
let's go back to our test I spoke about
2/3 tests and one taste test this is the
two taste tester represented with some
of our example with some more
information so again alpha the
significance is the risk of rejecting
the null hypothesis when when true
the value of 0.05 in this case for
Convention is split between the tails so
one of the area is is hard for alpha
alpha alpha the population is the one
that confirms the null hypothesis so the
population is the one in which the other
time for novices is equal to the average
time of experts while in the two tails
in the so-called rejection rejection
region I have the alternative hypothesis
that the average time of knowledge is
different from the average time of
aspect and of course I want to fall
there
one of the areas in the case of the
one-tailed test the representation is
slightly different because in this case
I have another Patris that is the
average time to find box oh no this is
greater than or equal to the one of
experts so my null hypothesis is
represented on the right part of this
life so the average time of novices is
greater or equal than average time of
experts because this is my hypothetical
population which the null hypothesis is
true and I want to fall on the left tail
in this case as a home vention the value
of alpha is the entire entire area
entire area on the tails so 0.05 is this
whole area right is the the one tailed
test right is the opposite case okay so
the average time to find bugs of novices
is less than or equal the one of experts
is my null hypothesis so the one that I
really want to reject I want to show the
experts are our quicker are faster and I
want to fall in the in the right area
now let's pass so now we have understood
what water is the alpha value
significance value what is the one
tailed test and Tutte test but still we
didn't actually perform the real
experiment we didn't perform the real
test actually the experiment probably
was the experiment was already performed
but we didn't we just set up the test so
the p-value I said that a tester generic
the statistical test produced a test
statistic value at a statistic value
that depends on the type of tests I mean
in this example is the so called T value
each test always produce also a p-value
each single test in general since now
you have to remember that low values of
peak so low means around 0.001 are good
high values like higher than higher than
0.5 0.0 5
we will see our bad ok so the p-value
you already understand there is
something that needs to be compared with
my alpha
let's see graphically what is the
p-value we saw that alpha that was set
up before the experiment was is was this
area on the on the tail after doing my
experiment I can derive my test
statistic value that is here in the
x-axis and I can derive of course
another area the p-value is exactly this
blue area if this blue area is lower
than the alpha then the alpha area then
it means that my test statistic value is
a safe one is such that that I can
reject the null hypothesis because it's
so rare that I would fall here if the
null hypothesis was true that is more
likely that the null hypothesis was
false is false in the case of two-tailed
again as a convention we said that alpha
is divided by 2 in the true area and the
p-value resulting from from my from my
experiment it will be this blue area the
some of the blue area actually
so alpha and P are the sum of the area
in the two tails and alpha P are shared
basically between between the between
the two tails and mm-hmm
the test statistic value I ever derive
from the data falls just on one of the
tail you have just one one single value
when you when you do the test but this
is to let you understand how the p-value
works for both one tailed and two tailed
test and I think the graphical the
graphical explanation is pretty is
pretty clear so besides the graphical
explanation that I think is the most
intuitive way to understand the p-value
there are also different ways to
interpret it and to understand it from
other point of view let's read let's
read this three possible interpretation
the first one says the p-value indicates
the believability of the David
advocate case that the null hypothesis
is true given the sample data so how
believable is the case that null
hypothesis is true given my evidence I
want this to be as at least as least
believable as possible so as P as lower
as possible
the second way of explaining the p-value
is the p-value is the probability of
observing a test statistic that is at
least as Extreme as your test statistic
when you assume that the null hypothesis
is true again this is a similar way of
of interpreting the the p-value that
let's start from the idea that our null
hypothesis is true and I am observing a
test statistics that is very extreme
that is very uncommon in a population
when the null hypothesis is true when
the null hypothesis is true
the p-value at the third interpretation
the TV value the p-value indicates to
adjust and the results may be de memy
due to a random variation within your
data which make them different from the
actual population so this is another way
from another perspective if the actual
population is actually true the the
p-value may indicate that your data
actually full full and there because
they are because they are due to some
random variation in the data okay so the
T value is falling there because it's
still possible that very unlikely but
still possible that in a population
where the null hypothesis is true a
certain test would fall there okay
the conclusion is the people when the
p-value is very low the null hypothesis
is rejected in favor of the alternative
hypothesis otherwise if the p-value is
greater than alpha we say that I fail to
reject the meaning of very low depends
on the on the value of alpha so what I
search for is p-value my less or equal
than alpha and I search to fall on the
and I think this is clear to you I mean
I'm saying reject and fail to reject and
not accept and not accept because here
you have to consider that you are
inferring some information about an
entire population from a single sample
so if your single sample that is your
experiment is is different from it is
different from the the actual population
you know let's let's say it in another
way if you are you are comparing
basically a single sample with we want
to use the information from the simple
sample to you want to use the
information from the cincone sample to
infer some in conclusion some
information about the entire population
of course this cannot be something that
that confirms completely a certain
hypothesis but it can be say if if your
sample is so rare it can be sufficient
to reject the assumption so there are
some so that the null hypothesis is true
so that's why we are using this
terminology of rejecting and fail to
reject and not accept because it is
likely that your hypothesis is true but
to actually show that your hypothesis is
true you would need to repeat the
experiment many more times and show that
the actual distribution follow the one
order of the test that is to follow the
one of of the of your alternative
hypothesis last thing is the effect size
the effect size is another number that
is producing is produced throughout a
test not directly but a test but through
another to another computation this is
useful because something that is
statistically significant when
is less than or equal than alpha we say
that the results are statistically
significant but this does not imply that
there is a large effect and the effect
size measures how large is this effect
how big is this effect so how much is
the difference for example between
novices and experts to compute the the
effect size as I stick the data from my
experiment and I use a specific
approaches for computing the effect size
that in this case will be equal to 2 so
another number that is produced by the
test and that I need to interpret there
are several ways of computing this
effect size here I will give you some
point ok so FX size is a quantitative
measure of the magnitude of the
treatment so how much better is my tool
how much faster are the are the expert I
will faster at the aspect and the effect
size measure either the size of
association and relationship between
variable for example if I have a
question research question like the one
that is shown here like how much is
experience correlated with development
speeds so this is a relationship an
association or the size of the
differences between group means how much
is the difference between Thule MB this
is more related to to our example there
are several ways to measure the effect
size and but here I exemplify just to
because it's just a matter of of
computation Cohen's D is used for
differences Pearson R correlation is
used for relationship but it can depend
also on the type of data categorical or
numeric and on the type of sample if
they are paired or unpaired you can find
the specific effect size measure to use
in Wikipedia so take in your case your
example your your experimental case you
can select
in a deterministic way which is the
effect size that you should use like for
the test and but for the tester we
explain you better next in the next
lecture Cohen's D quantity indicates
that the difference between the means
device is the difference between the
means divided by the standard deviation
of the population from which the data
were sampled you don't need to
understand this in depth basically the
watch what you need to remember is that
quantity of one in the case that the two
group differ by 1 star the division the
quantity of 2 indicates that they differ
by 2 standard deviation and so on and
this is how you should interpret them
according to this table so this is 0.01
indicates that effect size is very small
D equals 2 to 2 indicates that the
effect size is very large
similarly for Pearson R that indicates
differently from Cohen's D indicates the
correlation between variable so for
example number of bugs in relationship
with the length of the of the code
sample here I have I have the value that
is between minus 1 and 1 the effect size
is low if Pearson R is around 0.1 media
medium if it's around 0.3 and large if
it's more than 0.5 so every time you do
an experiment you say okay my results
are significant and the effect size is
low medium or large of course you are
searching for large effect size so in
all our evaluations we have assumed that
the population was confirming the null
hypothesis and so we aimed at avoiding
type 1 error so rejecting the null
hypothesis when it was when it was true
but there is still a possibility that we
make it up to error so fail to reject
the null hypothesis when the actual
population rejects it so I fall closer
to the center of my of my of my
distribution but the actual population a
is actually in favor of the alternative
hypothesis in this case is to control
for this cases which established a value
that is normally called beta and is the
probability of accepting the null
hypothesis although it is false and is
associated beta as we saw at the
beginning which are two error if the
null hypothesis is false this real
this means that Maria population follows
the alternative hypothesis but I'm not
able to show that from my from my data
let's see how these are depicted
depicted in this in this diagram so we
had our distribution if our h0 our null
hypothesis would be true and we have the
other distribution still for the test
statistic that we would have if the
alternative hypothesis would be true
this would be positioned in different
part of my of my diamond different part
of my x axis okay
our alpha is the value associated to the
first distribution so the distribution
of the null hypothesis to ever-smaller
alpha i have somehow to push this bar
towards the right to reduce there or my
alpha the issue is that if I reduce
alpha I tend to increase the other value
beta beta which is the probability of
accepting the null hypothesis when this
is false and remember the Alpha is the
probability of rejecting the null
hypothesis when this is true so every
time I try to decrease alpha my test
statistic may fall in the may fall on
the on the left part of this of the
central bar and this may be also
associated by the case in which the
distribution h1 was representing the
actual population but I am not able to
reject the null hypothesis because if I
fall here in this red area
I don't reject I am not able to reject
the null hypothesis so they they trade
off the trade or a trade off must be
chosen normally we are oriented to
choose a smaller alpha also with the
risk of of not being on failing to
reject a null hypothesis in general this
is what is commonly done but the problem
is that whenever we try to minimize type
1 errors so reducing my alpha we end up
increasing the chance of type 2 errors
there's no there's no way that that you
can that you can balance in our case we
must look at rejecting the null
hypothesis so we focus on type 1 error
but I guess that from this diagram you
have understood what is the difference
between the two errors and what is the
trade-off consider that this line is the
line that comes out after you have
selected your alpha okay it's not really
a selection of a specific line is a
byproduct of the selection of the alpha
value so I choose the alpha value and I
have a line in a certain position and as
a consequence I will avoid so beta in
another in the India on the opposite
side finally at this point I think you
have understood why we look at rejecting
the null and not at let's say accepting
accepting the alternative the main
reason is that we are always thinking
about distribution but our experiment is
just one sample and this sample is used
to reason on an entire population so I
can reject a hypothesis or fail to
reject it but never accept it because
it's just one single sample if I would
like to accept the alternative
hypothesis this would imply that I need
to repeat the experiment many more times
and with different sample taken from the
actual population and show that my test
statistic follows exactly the
distribution of the alternative
hypothesis and this is very hard because
I have to repeat the experiment several
times so it's easier to show
that my experiment shows a t-value a
test statistic value that is so rare in
a population where the null hypothesis
is is true that is more likely that the
null hypothesis is incorrect is is false
so I can reject it but I'm never sure of
course
to be sure I would need to repeat my
experiments in a population many many
more times I think that this makes you
understand why we speak about this three
key thing of rejecting the null
hypothesis we and the all statistical
test is is based on rejecting the null
hypothesis is another more of such an
intuitive way to understand it is the
one that I've put here that is let's say
that it is easier to disprove that all
swans are white because I I need only to
find one black swan than to prove it
because in this case I need to check all
possible Swan and there is always a
chance I can hypothesize the chance that
there will be one one black black one
but less one in in my population okay
this is a the additional intuition too
to make you understand why with the one
sample I cannot I cannot say I accept a
certain a certain hypothesis a certain
eternity by politics okay
summary of key concept that you need to
remember whenever you perform an
experiment keep in mind this four
concept level of significance this is
alpha and tells me how much risk I can
take and every time in software
engineering is 0.055 and if he said at
the beginning of the experiment then he
said as a value before starting your
experiment based on the risk that you
are willing to take test statistic this
is the value that depends on the test
that you make and it serves to
understand how much my sample is rare in
a population in which the null
hypothesis is true
okay is the output of
your computation is the output of your
test and these produce based on your
experimental data this number alone
doesn't say much we will see some
example of T values that do not tell do
not tell us much what is important to
consider instead is another product of
the statistical test that is the p value
the p value indicates the probability of
rejecting the null hypothesis when it is
actually true it is produced - based on
my experimental data and it needs to be
compared with alpha if it is lower than
alpha then I am happy because it means
that I am able to reject the null
hypothesis in favor of the alternative
hypothesis finally the effect sides the
effect size indicates how large is the
difference between the two treatments or
how much is the correlation between the
independent and dependent variable so
differences or correlation and we said
it depends of the chosen test and there
are tables to assess how large is this
effect size here you have a graphical
summary and that I think is quite
intuitive you start from the data of
your experiment you select a
significance level you perform your test
this test will produce a test statistic
and as a by-product a p-value at this
point you compare with the p-value with
the significance value and if it's lower
or while you reject the null hypothesis
at the same time you have to perform the
effect size computation by taking the
data of your experiment and compute the
effect size and compare it with the
typical value of effect size and decide
whether your effect is small or large
and this it is easy