okay in the previous slides I showed you
the an overview basically of what what
you are going to learn through this
course and mainly not really an overview
because you didn't see so much about the
methodologies but more of the motivation
why the thing that I would present you
in this course are irrelevant I
mentioned during the presentation that
we will have to deal with with several
stakeholders and I mention different
activities in the software engineering
process that are development testing etc
now let's see which which ones are the
roles that you would deal with in this
that you will deal with with the
different methods and the tasks in the
software engineering process this is
just a very very very broad overview
okay we chart the roles roll it software
engineering are different they change
based on the process also that you may
have in a company they vary on the
dimension of the company I will not I
will always repeat it until you are
tired that every company is different
every context is different but in
general a software engineering company
or a software company always have at
least the developers that are the ones
who do the coding of course this could
be also in principle outsourced because
I may be a company that have some that
doesn't develop in-house but is just
combining the code developed by
different developers outside but in
general in some way developers as always
him are always involved sometimes so you
may have designers and architects so
designers an architect I'm reading in
the slide from the bottom and like
checking some roads somewhat randomly
designers and architects are the wise
design the system at a high level and
the ones who do the project basically
very often is more company these are the
same as developers so-and-so or they
don't even exist if you are if you are
in a company where you are you don't
design the software but you simply
incrementally develop it so you don't
have this this type of roles okay you
add the requirements or business analyst
we would see the requirements engineer
business and several names are used for
that functional analysts in some cases
and this is the ones that gather the
requirements from customers and users
and create their requirements documents
to be used by the developers but very
often this is just a guy that interact
with the customer and doesn't write down
the requirements document but simply
speak with the developers to say what
they should do or write down the
so-called user stores that are short
form of requirements if you are using
so-called
agile processes okay then you have the
users the one that will use the system
and the customers the by the ones who
buy the system these are also in the
scope of our interest what is the
difference between customers clients
that say and uses normal users are the
actual users for example in the example
that I made in the previous part of the
lecture in which I was considered and
hoskin see during a hospital the user of
the system to update information about
the coronavirus are actually the doctors
so the general practice doctors the
so-called Medici de Familia in Italian
these are the users of the system but
they don't they don't pay for the system
and they don't pay for the development
of the system the customer is actually
the
they have the Health Organization they
held company for example the hospital or
if you are dealing with the if you want
to deliver this product to the wall
settle Ospital in tuscany for example it
will be the region so you have different
subjects that have different needs
because the user probably in this case
don't care about the the price of the
software while the customer does and in
some cases the users are also customers
for example in case there of mobile
application of any consumer softwares
for example if you think netflix
software we're all users but we pay for
it
and we're also customers so but have you
ever have you ever met someone from from
netflix asking you what is what is your
need for good bit in the system it
didn't happen
so you ever roll but you don't interact
directly with them but they can
understand what you did by sampling from
from your interaction with the system
they try to understand when you are
watching those movies which type of
movies are you watching and they
understand what are your needs based on
the usage of the system and this is
typical of for many consumer products
like for example Netflix or any app that
you have in your mobile or Microsoft
Word or any of this type of code summer
pro consumers products that that I used
by mmm that are used by by people that
are oriented to the large market and are
not specific for solving a problem like
the one I said for the hospital or for a
chain of supermarkets for itself if the
company is large you may have also some
managers in general you distinguish
between three levels of management in a
large company you have top-level
managers which are responsible for
controlling oversees the entire
organization so this is a top level
meet the level which are responsible for
executing organization plans according
to the company policies and they are
basically intermediate towards the top
management and low-level manager that
are ever direct contact with the
developers they say and often they are
called
project manager okay they ever there are
role models for the employees they
supervise and they control the timing
and they do more fine-tuned to control
but they don't give let's say the the
decision for the decision for a more
larger plan they are focused on a
project or two projects and they direct
the specific projects but there are more
level of management of all above them
and then there is the Board of Directors
so it's a people group elected by the
stockholders possible if if it is a
company if it is a market company and
they decide corporate policies and make
management decisions normally when we
study when we study software engineering
problems we don't do much with the Board
of Directors of course we may deal with
managers because the low-level managers
especially the project managers are are
dealing with the software and they are
really relevant roles we deal with
customers we use it with requirements
business scientists sometimes will
report designers and architects although
many companies don't have them and we
developers and testers so testers are
the ones who test the code so the
subjects that may be also or subjects
who review the code this is the review
the code they simply don't test but just
look at the code and check for the
quality this may be often the developer
themselves so everything may be adapted
to a specific company's need but these
are the main Rosemere names that you
will
that you will hear and you will read
about in software engineering
publications as I said companies may
include the only a subset of the roles
some of the roles may be covered by the
same person
so as I said some testers may be
actually developers some code reviewers
may be actually developers or the
designers may be the developers and in
some cases even the business analyst may
be the developers and the role may
depend of the adopter software process
so there I didn't go through this
disaster but there are two let's say
general general paradigm of software
process one is the traditional software
process that is the so-called waterful
process and in which you have the
sequence of steps like the one that I
described so you start from the
requirements you start with the
interaction with the customer you write
the requirements you design the software
you write down the code you test it in
etc etc or you have the so called guides
of the process and that is the more
modern way of programming of developing
software that consists in having
frequent interactions and frequent the
delivery of prototypes and rapid
implementation so the you don't wait to
develop you don't wait for the entire
requirements document to be completed or
the design to be completed before coding
but you start prototyping Cinda bit
since the beginning and you have
frequent stand-up meeting with the other
partners and you have more relevance of
interaction between between people so
rows may depend on the way that you
decide to develop your software which
are the main tasks the main tasks you
saw them in the in the previous in the
previous
in Denisha slides but I want to
emphasize them in here because the
examples that I will give throughout the
world the world class that will deal
with this aspect so when I speak about
requirements elicitation and analysis I
speak about the first phase in which you
try to understand what is needed to be
built
okay so requirements elicitation and
analysis is a very vast area and may
have different practical practical
solution in the sense that as I told
before you may have situation in which
you interact directly with the customer
so with the people who will pay you for
your product or you may build a consumer
product and so you have to harvest
gather the requirements from from the
mass from the people or just rely on new
ideas internal and then test these ideas
that are internal to your compendious
test this idea with the people of course
they didn't ask people for the iPod or
they didn't ask people for when they
invented the car so many new invention
also in software they come from ideas
and observation of reality and don't
need to require a direct interaction at
least at the beginning with the user but
it has been demonstrated that the
involvement of the users since the
beginning may be really useful to test
your idea I understand that you're not
wasting your money in the in the
investment that you are doing software
architecture software so this
requirement solicitation and analysis
analysis means means several things
means try to structure the requirements
imagine for example the requirements for
a system that is built on the trains
that you are using you may be using not
now how much usually the system that
brakes the train in case the driver
exceeds with the control speed
the requirements for these are like 300
or 400 pages long and this is just one
part or the more technical required and
you have different volumes that specify
how this software the different parts
related to the risk to them today other
aspect let's say of the process but it's
like a very large volume and analyzing
these requirements means that first
you've gone through the process of
starting from more abstract requirements
let's say then you have formalize them
and then you have checked that there is
no ambiguity in these documents that
they have being that they are clearly
understood by anyone who reads them etc
okay so the analysis process success
especially for very complex systems is a
very safety critical system like the
trains or aircraft is very it's very
long this this phase in which you try to
understand them formalize in written
form your requirements then you have the
software architecture software
architecture was what I what I was
speaking was so before about that is
design and softer so creating the the
picture of your soft train you I met
before you implement it UML is the most
common way of designing your software
software architecture of course that
there is a distinction between software
architecture and design because
architecture is more high level while
design is more related to object
oriented design let's say so it's more
detail why the architecture should be
language independent normal so doesn't
rely on objects and this type of stuff
but for what we are interested here
software architecture is building
somehow a model of what will be the
structure of the software that satisfies
the requirements that I am licit it so
if the development is the actual act or
developing that is not simply opening
the computer and start writing the code
is also interacting with the other
developers interacting with the software
architects interactive with the
requirements elicitation fair with the
requirements analyst so interacting with
several other subject and writing down
what the software should do but also the
bug in the sauce because of course when
you write the software you into it it
doesn't it doesn't always work properly
but also refactor the software so I mean
it - I find a bug that effects a certain
part of the software I need to refactor
it or I need to refactor the software
because new requirements come from the
customer can have several cases of
course then you have software testing
software testing also in this case you
may have different levels of testing for
example you have only a function level
you have only to do unit testing for a
Java program so you test just that unit
according to a set of tests or you may
need to do integration testing
integration testing means that for
example for the system that I was
exemplified before for stopping the
training case there is a the driver
exceeds the the maximum speed in that
case I may need first of all one system
that is on board but the system has to
be linked also to the brake so I need to
integrate probably the software that is
directly controlling the brake with the
software that is in this other box and
antis is monitoring the speed of the
train and in addition in this
architecture am I also have some
software that is deployed deployed on
the ground that is sending for example
the status of the Signet so the
semaphores that you that you meet across
the line so i have to integrate it to
check that all these elements interact
properly and this is so-called
integration testing
not this real same thing of the of the
unit testing which I test a function but
still I'm doing an a testing activity
and this is of interest for for for
software engineering and for our scope
then there is software documentation is
something that is normally poorly done
but in some cases is mandatory so it is
for example when you are developing
safety critical systems you have to
document each step of your of your
process and you have to careful the
human chess software super so writing
down the the what the software is doing
and if you if you are if you are
developing also man wants for example
for users or man was for developers also
how the software should be used and how
it should be extent and maintained and
then you have software maintenance
software maintenance is the other phase
in which okay I need to update the
software based on new requirements
normally the software developers are
involved in here but the activity is
completely different because I have to
refactor normally software do small
changes debug etc and finally there is
the software process management as a
short in the beginning of the
presentation there is a process this
process need to be managed by somehow by
some but as some people I've shown three
level of Management and these three
levels are involved in checking that the
word process runs smoothly but software
process management is also dealing with
concurrent versioning systems dealing
with bugs bug report dealing with all
the older tools and echo and and system
that allows me to better manage my
softer so summarize in software
engineering we are dealing with all the
roads that I listed in this previous
slide
in with all these roles from managers to
customers to uses to requirements
analyze to designers to developers and
testers
and more you I will show you more
details on the role when we will speak
about surveys which are more focused on
people so you need to understand more in
detail what are the roles and these are
the tasks so these people and these
tasks so we will deal with station
architecture development testing
documentation maintenance a software
process management you don't need to
learn in depth what are all these phases
what I told you now should be sufficient
to have a sufficient understanding
because here we are focused on tasks and
people but mostly on methodological
aspects so let's pass to this other part
and this will be the last the last part
for for today that is related to one of
the core one of the core element of
research that is the formulating
research questions so basically anything
that that you do in research in software
engineering but also in any type of
research starts with a question about
the reality ok a question about the
world this is normal in software
engineering a problem to solve
so the question about the word is how
can I solve this problem but it can be
also curiosity about some of surveyed
fact this curiosity is often related to
something that you that you feel is
relevant but you you cannot say why for
you is relevant and for example it is
interesting to know why do developers
prefer to work at night isn't it it's
something interesting but why is it
interesting why you are asking this
question you really don't know but
probably if if you understand why for
example by interviewing set of the
you may understand that these will help
you in in better in better plan your
software process in better define for
example your schedule for for your
company because if you find that
developers prefer to work at night so
why should you force them to work during
the day why should you have a strict
strict timing or if you discover that
this is not true and some people prefer
to work at night some people prefer to
work during the day
why don't you profit from that for that
from that and you start having some
people working during the day and some
people working during the night so you
have 24 hours people working and it can
be also some curiosity about some
unknown fact so some unknown fact this
is the curiosity about something that
you may have observed so you have an
intuition and you are curious to know
but also you want to know something that
you don't know sufficient you want to
explore so for example what are the most
frequent effects in open source code
which are their most typical the the
fact that you can find in open source
code this can be a vague curiosity you
don't know why it's interesting but you
may be interested in that the research
question is the inquiry that guides your
research so it's a question written in
natural language when I say natural
language I say means English Italian any
language that you normally use a spoken
language or written form in this case
and the research question can be
something like which are the most
frequent effects in code developed by
people with less than six months of
experience so by novices this is a
research question also which are the
most frequent effects in the code
developed by people from six months to
three years experience so this is
another research question a search
question is something that it's written
is clear and guides your research and
you should always refer to it to design
your research
you know my structure your research and
reporting according to one or more
research question writing them down can
help you to clarify your goal and also
not just to you but also to the reader
because you do research but you have to
communicate it of course because anytime
anytime you you research research for
something if you don't communicate it is
useless okay it's just useful probably
for you for your knowledge but it's not
useful for the other researchers or the
other software engineers normally if you
have more than one research questions
it is good to establish their general
research question or research objective
so for example if I want to consider how
aspects so how things are in practice so
more curiosity about observable fact I
can ask myself to eat just answers and
effect types are related to the degree
of experience of the developer this is a
general research question and the other
two question that you saw at the
beginning on slide so which are the most
frequent defects in code
developed by people with less than six
months experience and the other question
about the facts they encode developed by
people that are older this can be
summarized with a more general research
question is quite intuitive like to
adjust and certain defects type are
related to the degree of experience of
the developer I want to understand the
relation between degree of experience
and defect I because my idea is that no
of these people tend to introduce more
of a certain kind of defect while older
people tend to do mistake that are more
or less a at architectural level but I
can also introduce a more general
question also related to this like that
consider also why aspects for example
which is the relationship between the
defects types and degree of experience
of the developer so this is more vague
okay is not just that I'm searching
for relationship between the fax type
and degree of experience I'm also and
trying to understand what type of our
relationship is there in a broad sense
so why for example people that have less
experience do certain type of defects
and in this case probably I need to go
further and not just do an experiment
for example in which I have young people
odd people and let them program and see
the defects that they make and in order
to interview them and to ask them why
they committed a certain defect and to
check with them for some motivation that
can make me better understand the
relationship between the effect type and
degree of experience of the developer
okay this is a something quite difficult
to grasp but I invite you to to reason
about that because the difference
between and between how things works and
why things works in a certain way is
very relevant and you need always always
you need to resort to a different type
of methods if you want to understand
both how aspects so how things are
related with the sort of correlation
that's a correlation function and why
aspects so find the human reason behind
certain phenomena so many times a clear
formulation of the general research
question comes after the formulation of
the most specific research question so
it is easier to write down which are the
most frequent effects in code developed
by people that has less than six months
experience because it's more practical
you know you know that you have to
select people will assign some months
experience but then you have to think
what is the thing that I want to
understand I want to understand
relationship between age and type of
defects and I
to understand also why there is if there
is a relationship this relationship
holds in some cases to distinguish you
can between like detailed research
question like the ones that I listed
before and the more general research
question you can sometimes formulate the
general research question as a research
objective so instead of a question just
a sentence like the objective is
understanding to each stand a certain
defect types are related to the degree
of experience of a developer so this is
what is my research objective how do I
pack it into partition it into different
questions yes I start with the first
questions which are the most frequent
effects for people with six months
experience the most recurring the first
with people with between six and three
six months and three years and then I
can add the other other question for
people who have who have more who have
more experience and finally answering
the general question that will tell me
which are which is actually the
relationship between the the type of
defects and the years of experience here
I will I will tell you how to to write
down I will give you a guide that is
taken from Robert felt you can check
this PDF inning in Internet that is is
free that is very simplified guide to
how to formulate research questions it
is very important it is not important
really to let's say to to remember this
graph this structure but it's important
to refer to possible example actually of
research questions but of course
didactic li-like for for teaching you
for teaching you the different types of
research question is very useful to have
this classification okay so we have a
first of all research question in
software engineer you have to type as I
told you at the beginning for
we need to understand the reality and
then we build a solution so my research
question can be knowledge for Houston so
understanding the reality or solution
focus so the objective is transforming
the reality okay let's start with the
knowledge focused noise focus can be
exploratory so I don't know much about
the phenomenon and the studies I want to
create some tentative series I want to
try out some hypothesis and I want to
give evidence for example that a certain
phenomenon that I want to study can be
made measured for example the consumes
question should be general is
exploratory it's a new thing that I
don't know anything about for example to
which extent do developers get tired of
coding I still don't know if they get
tired of coding okay and I still don't
know why they make a tile coding so this
to which extent is a simple way of
saying hey explore this theme explore
this topic okay then I have a base rate
question base rate question and when you
already know something about certain
phenomenon we want to understand out the
phenomenon and the study appears which
are the normal patterns and this can be
asked when you already know a little bit
so you know that people are able the
people tend to get tired of coding my
more detailed question is about
frequency when the developer gets out oh
god okay so I ask I ask myself something
about related to the base rate that can
be frequency or can be process we'd see
more more example later on other so this
in the first case in exploratory case I
don't know anything now I know that the
certain phenomena happen and can be
measured so I asking a base rate
question in a different stage
the research and then I can also ask a
more detailed question like for example
how certain phenomenon under study
relates to other phenomena so why do
developers get tired of coding I asked
myself so which are the cows causes as
you see there is already causality there
which are the causes of for people to
get tired of coding ok these are
different levels that for knowledge
focus question that I normally reached
when you have different degrees of
knowledge of a system theme then you
have solution focus questions and
basically they describe better ways to
solve a problem or a certain situation
so which strategies app to achieve a
certain certain goal how can we refine a
certain tool to achieve certain goal in
a better way so they are related with
creating the new solution or refining an
existing solution these are still
research question as I told you before
because I need to find a way I need to
create an importance for a solution and
I have to test the hypothesis against
the reality like in the example before I
have to check that my proposal of
forbidding the people to work at night
actually reduces the number of bug in my
code and doesn't create new new problems
ok so here you have the different
subtypes I leave you I leave you this
this from from the from the work of
Robert felt that that is linked in this
light and I related to exploratory
questions can be of three types like
system descriptive and comparative so
existence is thus this phenomenon exists
so as I told before
that do people get tired of coding or
not is this thing that software
engineers really do like for example is
documentation something that they really
do because in a survey I may have in an
interview I may have understood that
these people are really really annoyed
by the fact of writing down
documentation and they say that is one
of the most time consuming activity of
the world but do they really document
the software and this is often not the
case so asking this this type of
existence question is important also for
understanding which one is the is the
reality okay for certain phenomena
actually existed deserves to be studied
descriptive descriptive cases are more
related to properties and attribution
thing that I can measure of a certain
phenomenon like what are the properties
attributes of a certain phenomenon for
example when it is is it is it is it
free not frequent but for example how
long is the documentation that they
produce for example and in any case the
things that are related to not to the
existent busted a discrete general
high-level description of a certain
phenomenon and comparative like how can
a certain phenomenon differ from another
phenomenon then you have the base rate
as I told there are can be related to
frequency of or to the process so how
often or how does this phenomenon
normally normally occur then you have
the relationship that are again very
similar to the exploratory they are
similar to inspiratory but instead of
focusing on a single element they relate
to
multiple elements for example do
occurrence is the of X correlate with a
certain other phenomenon or what are the
reason for a certain phenomenon do I
know that a certain phenomenon cause
causes another cause or prevent another
phenomenon and more related to actual
causes so causality related question can
be comparative of context related until
you have a couple a couple of examples
so these are just a list of typical
example of question can guide you in
better formulating the research question
this is quite important for you because
it would be part also of the exam to be
able to formulate research questions
okay so please pay attention to these
consider this material try to formulate
research questions and try to give your
own example and understand what is they
their classification as I said the
classification is useful to to give you
a way of of making sense of the
different types of question but in the
end it is useful to look at examples ok
this list of examples if you replace the
X and the y with some phenomena of
interest for software engineers they
they can be really useful for you how to
create research question you create
research questions by starting from not
a well-defined research objective
because as I said before it usually come
afterwards with the topic normally so it
can be software development speed and
then you can ask yourself do you want to
create more a better understanding or
you want to solve something related to
development speed if you want to create
better understanding then you are
dealing with a knowledge-based question
and you want to ask yourself something
like what effects development speed how
can we measure development speed so how
can we measure how fast are the people
in developing
what if then I have to ask myself okay
I've understood that I have a
knowledge-based question I have to
understand how much is known about this
specific topic if not much is known I
have to ask an exploitative question so
how can we measure for example
development speed because this is also
problem for example how can we measure a
little in relation to what in relay in
relation to the level software that even
good software for example which are the
measures that I can put into place okay
then you can have more information so
you know asset the phenomenon of
development speed but you don't know
when certain sentence when or how it
occurs so what is the development speed
actually of a child tips so specific
types specific types of teams and I want
to measure the I want to measure in this
specific case what is what is their
development speed in the case in which
you know the phenomenon and you have
understood it quite correctly how things
work in practice so you can measure you
can note also how things are working so
you've been able to measure for example
the develop speed of agile team you may
want to understand what is affecting
development speed so why certain teams
are faster than others so in this case
you want to understand the relationship
before between certain unknown causes
and the development speed in cases that
you've working towards a solution based
question the question can be how can I
improve development speed what is the
easiest way to improve the variable
speed you see that there is a
relationship now first as I said before
knowledge so first you understand what
effects development speed and then you
ask yourself how can I improve it how
can I move the factors so that
development speed increase
what is the easiest way to improve
development speed so which factors can I
use to somehow tune it so for example
pair programming I can use another
language or I don't know I can make
people work at night work at the time
that they want I can remove the presence
of the program manager I don't know
after I've studied the factor I can put
in place a solution that solved my
problem normally as I said before one
research question is not sufficient and
you normally need multiple question so
try to find after you have written down
some base question try to find the main
research question or overarching
research objective and then keep on
refinement the your type of question
okay and check the types of question the
previous table and adapt them to your
problem too so you start with the
question and you refine it you refine it
okay you refine it you you first go up
to more higher level research objective
and then go back and refine again so to
understand whether you've covered your
actual research objective and just in
the end very often just at the end of
your research you finalize the research
question this is something like they
seem to come at the beginning they
should come at the beginning at the
beginning you write some research
question but it is true that every time
you do an experiment every time you do a
case study anytime you study a real
phenomenon you understand that your
question need to be changed so your
research objective and your research
question will because stable just at the
end just like the requirements like the
requirements for a system they become
stable just when the system is finished
also the research question they get
transformed and transformed still even
in their form intermediate form they are
needed to guide your process so this is
this is all for for today
and we will we will meet again on on
Thursday