(water running)
(bass thumping beat)
- Do you hear that?
That's the sound of all
your Upwork connects
going down the drain,
because you're submitting
the wrong job proposals.
But don't worry, 'cause in this video,
I'm gonna give you 10 steps,
10 steps that you can implement
to help you save your Upwork connects,
and to ultimately, submit
the right job proposals.
If you've been freelancing on Upwork,
then you're aware of the
recent connects policy change.
This new policy changes how
Upwork connects are required
when you're submitting a job proposal,
and also increases the price of connects
if you are to run out of them,
and want to purchase more.
So now when you submit a
proposal, it's going to require
one to six connects,
and that's gonna depend
on the specific job, so the type of job,
the estimated value of the
job, the duration, the budget.
All those things are gonna factor in
to how many connects are required.
For example, say you have a
job with the budget of $40.
and you have one with $1,000.
The job that has $1,000 budget
is gonna require more
connects than the $40 budget,
and then for the price of Upwork connects,
those were increased to 15 cents apiece,
so if you run out of your Upwork connects,
and you want to purchase more,
they're gonna be 15 cents each.
So I know your initial thought may be,
Upwork's just doing
this to make more money.
They're just trying to
increase the prices,
make it more difficult freelancers,
and make more money.
But let me a perspective that
you need to be thinking about
from a client perspective.
One of the main issues for Upwork clients
is feeling overwhelmed
and not being able to find
the best talent because
of how many job proposals
are being submitted for their jobs.
When a client has to scroll through
numerous amounts of job proposals,
trying to find the best fit for them,
it gets overwhelming when they're having
to go through so many.
Trust me, I have an
Upwork employer account,
so I know that a lot of job
proposals that come through,
should not be coming through.
A lot of them aren't taking
the time they need to take
to make sure they're applying for the jobs
that give them the best chance
to actually win the job.
They're going through with low effort,
submitting a bunch of proposals,
thinking that hey, if I submit
a large number of proposals,
I'm gonna get one of these jobs.
That does not work, and
you're never gonna get a job,
if that's your mindset.
So when you think about
this connect policy change,
think about it in terms of the client,
and yourself as a freelancer.
It's beneficial for both ends.
The client won't have to scroll through
as many job proposals from
a bunch of freelancers,
who shouldn't even be
bidding on their job,
and therefore, your
benefit as a freelancer,
your job proposal is
gonna be ranked higher
because you're gonna
be submitting proposals
on jobs that best fit
your skills, best fit the
requirements, and it's gonna
give you a better chance
to rank higher and be
noticed by the clients,
so in this video what I'm doing for you,
is I'm gonna give you 10 steps to take
before you submit a job proposal.
These 10 steps are gonna make sure
that you're submitting
the right job proposals
to give you the best chance to win a job
over other freelancers.
Before we get into the 10
steps, I ask one thing of you
if you get value from this video,
it's beneficial to you,
and you enjoy the content
and all the freelance content
that I'm putting on my channel,
please give this video a like,
and consider subscribing
to the channel as well,
so you don't miss out
on all my future videos.
Also be sure to check out the
description of this video.
There's gonna be a link in it
where you can go, enter
your email address,
then you can download a free PDF checklist
that's gonna have a lot of the steps
that we're talking
about here in this video
for submitting a job proposal.
It's a checklist that you can go through
each time that you're
submitting a job proposal
to make sure that you're
not skipping anything,
so again it's completely free,
it's down in the
description of this video,
just click on the link.
It'll take you to a web page,
you enter your email address,
and then you can download it.
Step number one, fully read the job title
and the job description.
After coming across a job title
that falls within your skill set
and looks like something you can do,
make sure that you're reading
the entire job description,
the full job description,
read it all in detail.
Sure, I get it.
This is something everyone should know,
but it's something
that's easily overlooked,
and I know that from my
own personal experience.
In my early days freelancing on Upwork
I focused way too
heavily on the job title,
I would apply for jobs
without reading the full job description
because I saw the title,
and it looked like something I could do.
So what ended up happening
as a consequence,
I either never heard back from the client,
never got an interview,
or I got an interview,
and we got on a phone call,
and I realized I didn't
have all the skill set
that they needed because
I didn't go through
the full job description,
and I know that if you've
been on Upwork for a while,
you know exactly what I'm talking about,
you'll see a job title.
Oh this is perfect, this
is definitely something
that's within my skill set.
I'll find something that says like
sequel server database administration,
and then I go and read
the job description,
and then there's things in there
like wanting to build a
front end application,
in C#, obviously does not fall
within the database aspect of it.
I know that you guys that have
been freelancing for a while,
know what I'm talking about.
So make sure that you're
reading the full job description
in detail, to save connects,
so you don't bid on jobs that
you don't have the skills for,
end up wasting your connects,
and wasting your time doing an interview,
you can applying that to a jobs
that you're actually qualified for,
and have the skill set for.
Make sure that you're reading
the full job description
to save your connects, and
on top of saving connects,
it also comes down to submitting
the right job proposals,
that's gonna get you the job,
and it's gonna lead you to
having a five star review
because you're not taking something
that you're not qualified for
and you don't feel comfortable
doing in the first place.
Step number two, check the skill level,
are you using appropriate filters
when searching for jobs and projects.
You need to be using
advanced filters and searches
when you're looking for Upwork jobs,
so that you're searching
for the right skill levels.
So before you submit a job proposal,
look at the desired skill level
that the client listed on the job.
If your skill level is
entry level or intermediate,
and you're looking at expert level jobs,
you may want to pay
close attention to that,
because you may not
have the desired skills.
In my personal journey as a freelancer,
when I first started, I had my skill set,
set to intermediate level.
I mainly did this because I
was brand new to freelancing.
I wanted to prove to myself
that I could be a freelancer,
and I wanted to be able to take on jobs
that I knew I could do well on
where the expectations
weren't set too high
at expert level, when I didn't
have any jobs completed yet.
Let's take a quick look at my
job history and my profile,
and I'll show you a couple of these jobs
that were intermediate level
that I started out on first,
and I ended up getting five star reviews,
because I delivered on them.
So here we are in my profile,
and I'll give you one quick tip
before we go take a look
at a couple of jobs.
So as you can see, my job success
score is currently at 99%.
Now the reason for this,
is because I have 30 jobs in progress.
I need to go through these jobs,
close out the ones that
aren't active anymore,
and just tell my clients that
if they have more work to me,
then they can just open up a new project
because they're always fine doing that.
So there are several things
that factor in your job success score.
You can highlight over it,
and if you click this link,
it'll give you descriptions
of each of these.
One of them is jobs in
progress that are inactive.
That factors into your job success score,
so mine basically consistently
goes back and forth
between 99% and 100%,
and it's always due to
my jobs in progress.
So every one of your
reviews could be five stars,
and pretty much all of mine are.
I have a couple that are like 4.8,
but basically you can have all
five star reviews like these,
but your job success
score will continuously
bounce between 98% and 100%,
because of how many inactive
jobs that you have open.
So you can join me and start going through
all your inactive jobs and
trying to get reviews for those.
But anyway, let's scroll
down and take a look
at a couple specific jobs.
Okay, so these first few jobs
were definitely expert level,
and you can tell that based on the money
that I made on them and the hourly rates.
But if we take a look at the next one,
we can see that this
one was for $27 an hour,
ended up making almost two
grand on it which is great,
and if we take a look at the date started,
we can see that I started
this job in August of 2016.
So I began my career on
Upwork as a freelancer
in May of 2016, so this was very early
in my freelance journey.
So we click on this job,
the first and most
important thing on this job
is that I got five stars on everything.
I got great feedback.
Let me tell you one thing,
if clients believe in you,
they trust you, you have great reviews,
the money will come.
Focus more on the reviews you're getting,
the trust you're gaining in your clients,
and all the money that
you want will come to you.
So in this job, I fully read the title,
fully went through the job description,
and then I checked the
skill level as well,
to make sure that time,
it was either entry level,
or intermediate, which is
what I was focusing on.
Then to show you one more job.
This was the first job that I ever had
on Upwork as a freelancer.
You can see that it was for $25 an hour,
ended up making $1,000 on it,
and it started in June of 2016,
right after I created my account.
Most importantly, again,
focus on this review
and focus on this feedback that I got.
This is so important when
you first start freelancing,
you need these.
If we click on this job,
again, fully went through the job title,
fully went through the description,
and we get down to the skill level
again entry level, intermediate,
that's what I was focusing on.
So make sure that you're
filtering and searching
for the right skill levels,
and if you don't know how to do this,
check out the card at the
very top of the screen.
I'm gonna link a video in
where I go through and explain
how to use Upwork search
and rank higher in search,
and within that video,
I go through and do filtered searches.
Step number three, check the
date and the time posted.
Before you submit a job proposal,
you need to check the date and time
that the job was posted on Upwork.
To give you a personal example,
when I first started on Upwork,
I didn't pay enough attention
to the day and time created.
What ended up happening as a result,
is that I submitted proposals
on jobs that clients
were no longer active on
and they had been posted a long time ago.
I just looked at the
title and description,
and decided it met my skill set,
and what I wanted to do on Upwork.
I submitted proposals, but the clients
weren't even looking
at those jobs anymore,
because they were created so long ago.
So let's go ahead and look
at a real live example.
I'm gonna show you an
example on Upwork right now,
of a job that was posted a long time ago,
that the client is not active on.
Okay, so here we are looking
for new jobs, scrolling down.
Oh wow, ongoing remote
position Sequel Server DBA
20 to 40 hours a week.
Wow, that looks amazing, a lot of work,
and this client's also
spent over $300,000.
I'm gonna go ahead and bid on this one.
So we can see that I did
submit a proposal here,
but just ignore that and
pretend that I didn't.
So we're scrolling down,
this job's still active by the way,
which is why I'm showing this to you.
So for the title, check,
definitely something I have
a ton of experience in.
But look at what we have
right under the title
posted seven months ago.
So I don't know about you,
but if a client posted a job
seven months ago, I'm gonna
assume that they're probably
not looking to fill this anymore.
But how can we verify this.
Maybe this job's just
been open for a long time,
but they're still actually
trying to find a good fit.
So here's what we can do.
We're gonna scroll down,
and boom, here we go,
activity on this job, second line down,
last viewed by client 17 days ago,
so they definitely viewed this job
within the past seven months,
from when it was posted.
However, they haven't even
looked at this in over two weeks.
Your odds of actually getting
this job, are pretty low,
and honestly, the odds of
them actually hiring someone
at this point for a job that's
been open for seven months,
and they've only looked at it
once in the past two weeks.
This is not worth the risk
of losing connects over,
trying to get this job.
The job's has been open way too long,
so be sure to check when
the job was actually posted,
and the last time that the
client viewed the job as well.
In the example that we looked at,
the client hadn't even looked at their job
in over two weeks.
That is a big red flag for me.
I'm not gonna put forth six connects,
up to six connects, trying
to beat on this job,
when they're not even looking at it.
Step number four, check the
number of proposals submitted.
When an Upwork job is fairly new,
and there's a low level of
proposals submitted for the job,
you have the best chance for
your proposal to get noticed.
Typically, I find it
best to submit proposals,
when there's only been
five to 10 submitted.
That's when you're gonna
have the best chance,
and again, this ties into why I think
the recent policy on Upwork
connects is a good idea,
the new policy is going to limit
the amount of spam submitting,
people submitting proposals
that they shouldn't be on jobs,
it's gonna decrease
the number of proposals
that are submitted for a given job,
giving you a better chance to get noticed
on the jobs that matter to you.
Again, a personal experience example,
I have an Upwork employer account.
I've hired freelancers to
help me with my business
and scaling things up.
So, when I created my job,
I started to get a bunch of
proposals pretty early on.
I had an short list, a few freelancers,
that I was really interested in.
So after about three or four days,
I had 20 to 50 proposals
submitted on the job
that I posted. Now, from
personal experience,
that was overwhelming.
I didn't want to take the time
to go through 20 to 50 proposals
to see if there was someone
better than the few freelancers
I already had shortlisted.
That alone is why this
step is very important.
You need to make sure that
you're applying for the jobs
that best fit your skills, fast
so you're gonna be
noticed by the freelancers
and get shortlisted
before all those build up,
but when you come across jobs
that look really intriguing to you,
they meet all your skills,
they meet all the check marks.
You take a look at that job,
there's 50 plus proposals
submitted on that job,
you need to take a hard look at it
and see if it's worth risking
your connects over that,
because especially if
you're a new freelancer,
and you get thrown into the
mix with 50 plus proposals,
your chance of being
noticed in all that mix
is going to be very low.
So for all the new freelancer,
I'll show you again what I mean here.
Here we are scrolling
down looking at jobs,
50 plus proposals, 50 plus proposals,
50 plus proposals, your chance
of actually being noticed
in that big group of proposals,
especially if you're a new
Freelancer, is extremely low.
I'm saying this to help you
not waste your connects.
I did this personally.
Trust me, you're gonna be wasting them
if you're bidding on jobs
that have 50 plus proposals.
That's so many proposals,
and yours getting thrown
into that huge mix of proposals,
there's just a low chance of you actually
getting that job,
and I'm saying this to
help you save connects,
so you can use those connects on jobs,
or you have a great chance
of getting hired and winning.
Step number five, check the number
of freelancers being interviewed.
Before submitting a proposal
it's also really important
to check the number of freelancers,
that are being interviewed,
and being considered by the client.
That means, if the client
is already interviewing some freelancers
who they shortlisted for
their job and favorited.
If they're already
interviewing these freelancers,
if you submit a proposal,
it has a less chance of being noticed,
and you getting an interview as well,
because they've already
narrowed their list down.
They've already found a few freelancers
who they're really
interested in and odds are,
they're gonna end up hiring one of those.
So again, let's quickly look at an example
of what I'm talking about.
So here we are in our list of jobs,
we're gonna scroll down,
and we'll click on this one.
Take a look at all the job details,
we're going down further.
Here we are, activity on
this job, interviewing five,
so they're already
interviewing five freelancers.
They also sent out eight invites,
they're probably
interviewing most of the ones
that they actually invited to the job,
so if you take a look at
the activity on a job,
there's a ton of proposals submitted,
they're interviewing freelancers already.
They invited a bunch,
your odds of actually getting an interview
and winning this job are pretty low.
Let me just show you something.
Is that worth losing six connects over?
Bidding on a job that already
has that many proposals,
that many people being interviewed,
are you willing to lose
six connects at a chance,
that's very, very, very low
of you getting an interview as well.
Step number six, check
the number of connects
required to submit a proposal.
Now this step, obviously,
is one of the main steps
and what a lot of this
video is geared around.
Now when you submit a proposal on Upwork,
you're gonna have to use
between one and six connects
unless the client invited
you to bid on their job.
If you receive an invite from a client
to submit a proposal, that
doesn't take any connects.
That's the way it was before.
That's the way it is now, you
don't have to use connects
if you're invited, but
for all the other jobs,
if you're going to spin a proposal,
you're gonna have to use
between one and six connects.
So on Step five, when
we looked at the example
I showed you at the top
where it showed the amount of
connects that were required.
For that specific job,
it required six connects.
So when you're going
through your checklist,
you're checking off everything,
you get to the connects,
if it takes six connects,
but everything's checking
off, go ahead and bid on it.
So when you're looking at a job,
and let's just say for instance,
this one takes six connects.
You're looking at the job,
things are checking off,
you get to a point where a couple things
aren't really checking off that well,
or you're really unsure if
it's gonna fit your skills,
and you're gonna have a
great chance of being noticed
by the client, if it's
gonna take six connects,
you might want to reconsider
if you should bid on that job or not.
I say that because a new job
that better fits your skills,
better checks off on everything
could get posted right now,
even as we're talking,
and you would have a better chance
of being noticed by the client,
getting an interview,
and ultimately winning.
Step number seven, check client reviews,
just like Upwork, clients
are gonna go to your profile,
they're gonna look at your reviews
and your feedback.
You need to do the same for the client,
meaning that you need to be
looking at their reviews,
and the feedback that freelancers
are leaving the client,
whose job you're interested in.
Obviously for new Upwork clients,
you won't be able to do this one.
However, for pre-existing clients
who've already been on Upwork for a while,
already worked with a lot of freelancers,
they're gonna have reviews
and feedback from freelancers.
I've personally worked with
over 88 different clients
on Upwork, almost all of them
have been amazing clients to work with.
However, there have been a
few very difficult clients
that I've worked with, and
you can ask any Freelancer
who's been on Upwork for a long time,
I guarantee you they worked
with a few clients that
were really difficult.
So to prevent putting yourself
in this type of situation,
what you can do is you can
look at the client's reviews,
go through those, see what freelancers
are saying about them,
about their communication,
about their professionalism,
go look at those reviews,
and again, let's take
a look at an example.
Okay, so let's look at a specific example
scrolling down, we're
gonna click on this job,
SRSS and Power BI Developer.
Taking a look at the right
hand side of the job,
we can see that this client has 22 reviews
and 4.98 average stars which is very good.
So let's scroll down and take
a look at some specifics.
Okay, so here's the client history,
let's look at what freelancers
are saying, awesome client,
great to work with, prompt communication,
clear in explaining requirements,
wonderful experience,
wonderful experience, five
stars, wonderful experience.
Again, tons of five stars.
Awesome client, always available,
great working with them.
A couple of bad ones,
but you can see they also left
the freelancer bad reviews.
So here's a great example of
when you probably want to look
at more than one review.
Three stars or less like this one
is definitely a bad review,
but we can also see that
they left the freelancer
a pretty low review.
If you take a look at
all their other jobs,
and they have all these five stars,
great reviews from freelancers.
Then odds are, the reason
why this Freelancer
gave them a bad review, was
because they didn't deliver,
and they knew that they were
gonna receive a poor review.
So that's something you might
want to look at as well,
but taking a look at
all the other reviews,
amazing work ethics, clear communication.
There's so many great
reviews about this client,
they would be a great one
to work with, in my opinion.
So just like Upwork clients are gonna be
looking at your profile to
see what other Upwork clients
are saying about you, and what
feedback they're giving you,
you need to be looking at the same thing
on the Upwork clients jobs as well.
You definitely want to be
in a great working relationship
with Upwork clients.
I have some of the same
clients that I've had
since I started on Upwork.
I have a lot of long term work from them.
Those are the type of jobs that you want,
they're gonna make you a lot of money,
you're gonna have a lot
of trust in each other.
So make sure you're looking at the reviews
of the Upwork clients to make sure
you're setting yourself
up to work with someone
that's gonna be great,
and someone long term.
Step number eight, check
hours per week, if hourly,
and also check the project length.
Before submitting a job proposal,
you need to ask yourself this question.
Do you have the availability
to accommodate the client's needs?
Now a lot of jobs are gonna
say, hours to be determined.
However, there are a lot of clients
that specify a certain amount of hours,
such as more than 30, less than 30,
so you need to be able to make sure
that your schedule is
going to accommodate that
and fit that type of requirement.
Then also for project length,
make sure that your
schedule, your availability,
is going to accommodate
the length to the project.
So if a client has a project length listed
as one to three months,
you need to make sure that for
the next one to three months,
you're gonna be able to
work on that project,
and I don't mean that you
can't do anything else
besides work on this project
for the next one to three months.
It means that for the
next one to three months,
depending on the hours,
depending on the scope,
all the deliverables that
you have to do for the job.
You need to make sure that for
the next one to three months,
you're gonna be able to fit
those into your schedule.
Now let's go ahead and take a look
at a specific example of where
you can view these things at
when you're looking at Upwork jobs.
Okay, so let's go ahead and
take a look at a specific job.
So scrolling down let's click on this one.
So here we can see that this job
is estimated to have more
than 30 hours per week.
So at 30 hours per week,
can you fit that into your schedule?
Do you have 30 hours a
week in your schedule
to free up for this job.
Then also the project
length, right beside of it,
more than six months.
So for the next six months,
is this a job that you
can keep working on?
Do you have 30 hours per
week for more than six months
that you can dedicate to a new job?
If you do great,
you can check this one
off on your checklist.
If not, then you probably
should not bid on this job
because you're not gonna
be able to accommodate
the requirements for hours
and the length as well.
So be sure to check both
the hour requirements
and the project length as well.
The last thing that you want to do
is win a job from a client,
start working on it,
not be able to fulfill
the hour requirements,
and the project length as well.
It's gonna leave a dissatisfied client.
It's gonna give you a bad review,
and that's something that you
really, really need to avoid.
Step number nine, check
preferred qualifications.
Upwork clients set
preferred qualifications
to limit and filter down
to the specific freelancers
and talent that they're
looking for to fill their job.
Now if you go to submit a proposal,
there's gonna be a red icon on
the preferred qualifications
if you don't meet those.
You need to take a look at
this, because you probably
shouldn't be submitting
a proposal on a job
that you don't meet the requirements for.
Upwork clients list those for a reason
because we're looking for specific talent,
specific freelancers.
If you don't meet those requirements,
and you still bid on it any way,
you're basically throwing
your connects away.
Let's take a look at a specific example
of what I'm talking about.
So again, we're gonna open up the same job
that we just looked at a moment ago.
Now scrolling down to where
the activity section is,
we're gonna see preferred qualifications.
So preferred qualifications
talent type, independent,
so this means that they want
an independent Freelancer
not an agency.
Job success score has to
be at least 90% or higher,
English level has to be
at least conversational.
Upwork hours, so this is how many
hours you've worked on Upwork.
They want someone that's
at least worked 500 hours.
Now if you don't meet these requirements,
let's say you had a job
success score of, like, 80%,
I would not bid on this job
because they're probably
not gonna give you a chance.
Now, for instance, let's say
that you don't have 500 hours
worked on Upwork, but you had somewhere
between 300 to 400.
If you met all the other
qualifications except for hours
but you were really close on hours,
then you could consider
still submitting a proposal
for this job because
you were really close,
and they may still give you a chance,
because you're really close
on the hour requirement,
and you checked off on everything else.
Step number 10, check the bid range.
Now for bid range, What I'm talking about
is the high, the average,
and the low rates
that freelancers are bidding on the job.
Now let's go ahead and take a look
at a specific example of
what I'm talking about.
So again, same job example,
we're gonna go ahead and click on it.
And now if we scroll down,
we can see the bid range.
So the high bid range on
this job is $61 an hour,
the average is $27.90 cents an hour,
and the low is $15 an hour.
So you can see on average
freelancers are bidding
around $30 an hour for this job.
So the next step to check in
combination with the bid range
is the skill level.
So this client is
looking for intermediate,
so they're looking for a
mix of experience and value.
So bidding $61 an hour
or higher on this job,
is probably too high and
not gonna give you a chance
to be considered, because it's higher
than the rate that they're
actually looking for.
So for intermediate skill level,
looking for experience and value,
they don't really have any history
where I can look at what
they've paid in the past
for similar intermediate skill level jobs.
Since they don't have that history,
what I would do is I would bid
somewhere between $27 an hour,
or maybe $25 an hour and $30 an hour.
If you hit that range,
you're probably gonna be
setting yourself up pretty well.
Again, this is an intermediate level job.
This isn't expert.
If this job were an expert level job,
you better believe I wd
be bidding a lot higher.
My hourly rate now is $100 an hour.
That's pretty much what
I do for everything
unless it's fixed price.
So, if you want higher hourly rates,
it obviously ties to the skill level,
and now for a bonus tip.
Once you go through the checklist,
you're looking at a specific job,
you start checking everything off,
everything checks off,
and you're ready to submit a proposal.
The first one to two
sentences of your proposal
is what the client is gonna see first.
So when an Upwork client
has a huge list of proposals
from freelancers, your
first one to two sentences
of your job proposal is
what they're gonna see,
and we're gonna take a
look at that right now.
I logged into my personal
Upwork client account
that I use, that I've
hired freelancers on,
we're gonna go in and
we're gonna take a look
at a proposal and see the first
one or two sentences of that proposal.
So now we're logged into
my Upwork employer account.
This is a job I created for
my YouTube video editing
when I was looking for a video editor.
I obviously hired Alex, who's
editing this video right now.
The guy was amazing.
I talk about him in a lot of my videos.
Anyway, this is his job proposal.
Let's go ahead and take a
look at that real quick.
Okay, so here's the first
one to two sentences.
Look at his cover letter
and his job proposal.
Hello, I'm a professional video editor
and motion graphics artist in Los Angeles,
and your posts jumped out at me.
Ideas for your channel and be yourself,
there's no one on earth like you.
So his first one to two sentences
were very appealing to me and
they grabbed my attention.
He briefly described
that he's a video editor
and motion graphics artist,
what I was exactly looking for,
also saying that my
post jumped out at him,
and then not only that,
but he offered ideas for my
channel right from the start.
So when you're orchestrating
your job proposal
and your cover letter, and
you're saying things like,
Hi, my name is Josh Burns.
I have this many years
of experience doing this,
blah, blah, blah, blah,
that's probably gonna get skipped over.
It's not jumping out at them obviously.
You need to be thinking in a way
to get the client to take action.
Write your first one or two sentences
to get them to take action, to
jump off the webpage at them,
get them to take action and get them
to look more into you as a freelancer.
So before you submit a
job proposal on Upwork,
make sure that you're
going through the steps,
go to the description in this video,
download my checklist, go
through it each time as well.
Not only will the steps
help you save connects,
and that's very important
now with the policy change.
What it's also gonna
do, it's gonna help you
submit the right job
proposals for the right jobs.
It's gonna give you
the best chance to win,
to win jobs over other freelancers,
to get those long term clients
that you're gonna make a lot of money on.
If you're not getting
jobs, don't look outward.
Don't look at Upwork and be like,
well I just couldn't get any jobs there.
it's too hard to get jobs there.
Don't look outward like that.
There's so many freelancers on Upwork,
who have made so much money,
I've personally made
over $400,000 on Upwork,
and I'm on pace to break
$500,000 this year.
There's so many other freelancers
who have made more than me.
All this stuff is public.
You can go search for
freelancers and view it yourself.
I've seen freelancers who
have made $600,000 plus,
a million dollars plus,
there's so many successful
freelancers on the Upwork.
So what do I do when things
aren't going well for me,
I look inward, what am I doing wrong?
What could I do better?
What can I change to give
myself a better chance
to win jobs and beat
out other freelancers?
You have to look inward.
If you keep looking outward,
you're never gonna improve.
You're always gonna be looking
for something that's wrong,
some type of excuse that
you can give yourself
for why you're not winning, and
why you're not getting jobs,
and when you're looking for excuses,
you're looking outward at
all the external forces,
you're gonna be giving half-assed effort
and not hitting your full potential.
I don't know about you, but I'm not okay
with not giving it my all,
with not trying to
reach my full potential.
I am not okay with leaving
things on the table
that later on in my life,
I'm gonna look back on
and be like, you know what,
I wish I would have went
a little bit harder.
I wish I would have grinded
I wish I would have taken more risk.
I'm not okay with that.
Make sure that you keep leaving comments
with your success stories as well.
I love hearing those,
and I want to keep hearing about those.
Take a look at Sylvio's right now.
He has been absolutely killing
it on Upwork as a freelancer.
He's watched my videos,
implemented my tips,
and now he's reaping all
the benefits from it.
Keep going, man and don't let up.
So if you're struggling to get jobs,
you're struggling with your job proposals,
you're struggling on Upwork in general
as a freelancer look inward.
What can you do?
What can you change?
Look inward at yourself,
that is gonna give you the best results.
When you start improving on
yourself, each and every day,
you keep making progress,
you keep getting better,
the results will come and
you're gonna make more money,
and more money, and more
money, as a freelancer,
and ultimately lead you
wherever you want to go.
Also be sure to check out
the description box's video.
I recently created a Patreon
account for the channel,
not only will it allow you
guys to support the channel,
and allow me to make more content,
and get over the one video a week
that I've been doing for you,
to get that up to two videos,
or even more than that as well,
but what it also provides you with,
are different rewards per tier.
Now these tiers include
things like poll based voting
on future content, so you'll
get the voice your opinion
on the content that I'm creating for you.
They also have rewards
like a monthly 10 minute
call with me to discuss
any freelancing questions
that you have, personal
development, and channel content.
I literally get so many DMs
about freelancing questions,
that I can't reply to all of them.
So this is a way for you guys be able
to support the channel,
and for me to answer any
questions that you have.
Then even higher level tiers
are gonna include things
like monthly Google Hangout sessions.
We're gonna have a group hangout session
to focus on training, and
discussion around freelancing,
and then channel content as well.
Then the highest level
includes a monthly one-on-one
Google Hangout session with me,
where we will cover a predefined topic,
we can go through your freelance
profile, your portfolio,
we will go over any freelancing questions
that you have to get
you set up for success.
So again, be sure to check out
the description box's video
for the Josh Burn's Tech Patreon.
Become a supporter of the channel.
I greatly, greatly appreciate it.
I love making content for you guys,
and I want to dedicate more
of myself to doing that.
I appreciate it, thank you.
On this end screen, I recommend
checking out these videos,
and be sure to hit that
round subscribe button
for weekly tag videos, and
hit that notification bell,
so you don't miss anything.
Thank you for watching
and until next time, yeah.
All I've got is tension man
Costs like a lot of buzz
Been stressing out I just can't
Got a a lot